<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Unpremeditated thoughts of the knowledge of God, whom to know, is life eternal. With some discoveries of the mysteries of creation, in the six days work, and the seventh days rest. : To which is added, a short discourse concerning those two great principles of natural philosophy, matter and motion. / Humbly offered to consideration, by one of the Philadelphia Society, who calls her self Irena.</title>
            <author>Institut de recherches européennes sur les noblesses et aristocraties.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing U92A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R185871</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077731</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077731</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151842</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151842)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2278:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Unpremeditated thoughts of the knowledge of God, whom to know, is life eternal. With some discoveries of the mysteries of creation, in the six days work, and the seventh days rest. : To which is added, a short discourse concerning those two great principles of natural philosophy, matter and motion. / Humbly offered to consideration, by one of the Philadelphia Society, who calls her self Irena.</title>
                  <author>Institut de recherches européennes sur les noblesses et aristocraties.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 156 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by T. Sowle, next door to the Meeting-House in White-Hart-Court in Gracious-Street, and at the Bible in Leaden Hall-Steet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Dr. Williams' Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Knowableness.</term>
               <term>Creation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151842:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Unpremeditated THOUGHTS Of the Knowledge of GOD, Whom to know, Is
LIFE ETERNAL, WITH Some Diſcoveries of the Myſteries of the Creation, in
the Six Days Work, and the Seventh Days Reſt. To which is added, A Short
Diſcourſe concerning thoſe Two Great Principles of Natural Philoſophy,
<hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Motion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humbly offered to Conſideration, by One of the
<hi>Philadelphia</hi> Society, who calls her Self <hi>IRENA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>T. Sowle,</hi> next Door
to the <hi>Meeting-Houſe</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court</hi> in
<hi>Gracious-Street,</hi> and at the <hi>Bible</hi> in <hi>Leaden
Hall-Street,</hi> 1697.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151842:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151842:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Moſt Illuſtrious And Excellent BENTIVOLIO My Unknown
Friend.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Illuſtrious Stranger,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>PArdon my giving You a Name, ſince You have not been plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
to make Your Self known to me by any: Pardon my not giving <pb facs="tcp:151842:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:151842:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:151842:4"/>You a Name and Titles which
might better ſuit Your High Quality: Poſſibly I might not ſee thorow
Your Diſguiſe. However, ſuffer me, <hi>Great SIR,</hi> to make Uſe of
this Ignorance to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver my not knowing how to converſe with a Perſon ſo
much Above me: I take the Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of Your Vailing Your Self, to Approach
You: As we can better behold the Sun when it <pb facs="tcp:151842:4"/>Vails it Self, than
when it breaks through the Clouds.</p>
            <p>Whatever might a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle hide Your Greatneſs, no Outward
Cloathing could hinder me from ſeeing the Excellencies of Your Mind: The Idea
I received of that, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged me to pay the ſmall Homage of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting
theſe Papers. The Mixture that is of mine in them, ſhews the <pb facs="tcp:151842:5"/>Darkneſs and Barrenneſs of my Mind; and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly needs Your Charity
and Humility to cover its Imperfection. What there is in them worthy Your
Obſervation, is not mine, but as it is Freely Given, and Paſſively
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived.</p>
            <p>If I have any ſight at all, I taſted a little of the Honey of
the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Canaan,</hi> and my Eyes are Enlightened; <pb facs="tcp:151842:5"/>My
blind Eyes have been Anointed with Eye-Salve; and I ſee, tho' it be but
little, Men as Trees.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Excellent SIR,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Accept this ſmall Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute; Accept it as an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of
Gratitude for the moſt High and Noble Favours: Receive it as the Greateſt
Act of Charity and Humility You can Exerciſe; eſpecially if <pb facs="tcp:151842:6"/>You
pleaſe to pardon my calling You my <hi>Friend,</hi> who am not Worthy to
be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The Meaneſt of Your Servants,</hi>
IRENA.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151842:6"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE <hi>Reader,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have no Great Man to preſent theſe few Sheets to,
whoſe Name might make them paſs into the World with more Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur: 
<pb facs="tcp:151842:7"/>It may be with ſome this might gain a little Eſteem or
Applauſe; But this I ſeek not.</p>
            <p>What is mine in this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is not worth Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to any
Body; What is from GOD, it is moſt fit I ſhould offer up to Him, with my
Self; Which I do Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Wholly, and Heartily.</p>
            <p>Receive from me, Lord, the All that Thou haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <pb facs="tcp:151842:7"/>me, which I humbly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate at Thy Sacred Feet; With a
Thank-Offering to Him that Lives and Reigns for ever and for ever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thou knoweſt not who I am; And if thou didſt know my Outward
Perſon, thou wouldſt know a poor vile con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible ſinful Creature. What
Treaſure I have, is in an Earthen Veſſel, that <pb facs="tcp:151842:8"/>the Power may
be known to be of God.</p>
            <p>If thou receiveſt any Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Reading this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, if
thou feeleſt any Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, give GOD all the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, who alone is
Worthy.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dear Reader,</salute> 
               <signed> I am <hi>Thine in our
Bleſſed and Glorious JESUS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151842:8"/>
            <head>Unpremeditated THOUGHTS Of the Knowledge of GOD.</head>
            <p>IT is the Duty of all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to know GOD, the bleſſed
Creator and Former of all things; and there is in Man, in his Creation and
Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, a Power innate or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent, of knowing GOD; and therefore the
very Heathens are left without excuſe if they know Him not: For the holy
Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle St. <hi>Paul,</hi> exhorting them to feel after him, if haply they 
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151842:9"/>might find him, tells them, <hi>He is not far from us, for in
him we live, move, and have our being:</hi> So that this is the firſt and
moſt univerſal Way that God hath vouchſaft Mankind whereby to know him,
this Principle of Light implanted by God in his Nature: And doubtleſs the
Heathen by turning into this Light, do find it increaſe; and they being
faithful to it, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a further Enlightning; as appears by ſeveral
inſtances we have of ſuch as have attained to great Knowledge of God, of
Themſelves, and of the Nature of Things. My ſcanty Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing affords me the
knowledge o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but few of theſe
Excellent Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but thoſe I have a little knowledge of, I very much
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire; as that Excellently Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, tho' Heathen Philoſophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151842:9"/>
               <hi>Hermes
Triſmegiſtus,</hi> who had ſo early a Knowledge of God, as before the
World was bleſt with (our Divinely Inſpired) <hi>Moſes</hi> his Writings,
the Excellent <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> had a profound Knowledge of God and Nature, as
who reads his Book (turning in to the ſame Light) will find: I ſhall only
inſtance in what he ſaith of holy Stilneſs and Silence, a thing which I
fear many Chriſtians are ſo unacquainted with, that they hardly know there
is ſuch a thing from their own Experience, tho' certainly it is the true
ground of all Spiritual Activity. Another that occurs to my thoughts is the
famed <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> who certainly knew much of God, and Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal
Nature; tho' ſome good and ingenious Men will hardly allow him any great
Character. But to ſhew their Skill in argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151842:10"/>or
ſometimes for want of underſtanding the deep Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy of the Ancients,
they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their own imagination as the ſence of ſuch a Philoſopher,
which, it may be, was foreign from his thoughts; and this fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of their own
they ridicule, and bring the Unthinking World into an ill Opinion of the Author
and his Writings, without juſt ground: As ſome Perſons, Sir <hi>Charles
Woolſley</hi> and others, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt Atheiſm, do menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s ſaying the World is Eternal, as a groſs piece of
Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm; indeed to ſay it is Eternal, in the ſence they make
<hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſpeak, is irreligious and irratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; to ſay the
World is Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in this mutable ſtate of Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Effects, Generation
and Corruption; but certainly the wiſe Antients had a more deep 
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151842:10"/>ſight than this, they ſaw the World had a Divine Eternal
Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal in God; and this and many more excellent Truths, they ſaw more
clearly than many of us, who have the Happineſs to be born in the Chriſtian
World, and to have the ſecond and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent way of knowing God by the
Revelation he hath made of himſelf in his written Word. We can never be
enough thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the ſacred Writ, that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men of old ſpake as they
were inſpired by the Spirit of God, and inſtructed us in the knowledge of
the Name, Nature, Attributes of God, in the myſtery of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
Production or Birth of the World; in <hi>Geneſis,</hi> Chapter 1. and many
other places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The bleſſed Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi>
ſaith, quoting the Heathen Poets, <hi>We are his Ofspring;</hi> the Holy 
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151842:11"/>Scriptures do alſo inſtruct us in the knowledge of Gods
Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Government of the World in many Ages and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, with the
Admirable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion, Beauty and Harmony of his Works and Ways of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;
an account of which the Scripture is full of throughout; and I might inſtance
in very many particular places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but this is done by excellent
hands who diſcourſe largely on this Subject, as <hi>Charnock</hi> and
others: we have alſo in Holy Writ an account of Mankind, his divine Original,
being made after the Image of God, in a Bleſſed State, a little lower then
the Angels; and alſo of his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable State that he by Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience fell
into, and became worſe then the beaſts that periſh: we have alſo an
account of the <pb n="7" facs="tcp:151842:11"/>moſt Admirable Work of the Redemption of
Mankind by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord; the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods our Bleſſed
<hi>Jeſus</hi> took (are diſcovered to us) by which this great Work was
performed for us, and alſo the operation of his Spirit in us; all theſe
admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Myſteries are delivered to us with that Authority, Majeſty,
Sweetneſs and Love, that we can never be enough thankful for them: But O! How
ſhort are we in our underſtandings of them? How little acquainted with
their Worth and Excellency till we receive the third and laſt Bleſſed
Help afforded by God to poor Mankind, his own Holy Spirit, by whom our minds
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Enlightned in the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God and of our ſelves, and by being
Illuminated by the ſame Spirit which the Holy Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151842:12"/>were
Inſpired with, we come to have the Scripture open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us clearly; and
indeed though of our ſelves we know nothing as we ought to know, yet in this
Spirit we come to know all things; for the Spirit ſearcheth all things, even
the deep things of God, and ſhews them unto us: our Bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
tells us in <hi>John</hi> 16. v. 12. &amp; 13. <hi>I have yet many things to
ſay unto you, but you cannot bear them now; howbeit, when the Spirit of Truth
is come, he will guide you into all Truth, and he will ſhew you things to
come:</hi> Now it is our duty to attend to this Voice of God in us, to the
Teachings of his holy Spirit, who is an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter, one of a Thouſand:
Thoſe things in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, and other Scriptures, hard to
be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, are made eaſie by the <pb n="9" facs="tcp:151842:12"/>teachings of this
Spirit; the Lord did ſtrive with the old World by his Spirit, in the minds of
men; there was not many Preachers in thoſe days; but <hi>Noah</hi> we read
was a Preacher of righteouſneſs, he preached by his Faith, which he
ſhewed forth by his Works: Tho' the Lord hath been from the beginning,
ſtriving with Mankind by his Spirit, yet this is the time when we have the
greateſt Encouragement to pray and wait for this great Bleſſing, as the
Fruit and Effect of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection and Aſcenſion of our bleſſed
Saviour, who aſcended up on high, that he might give Gifts unto men, this
great Gift of the Father, his holy Spirit. Our Lord choſe ſome to be
Witneſſes of his Reſurrection and Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; he hath alſo made
ſome able to witneſs to this effect of <pb n="10" facs="tcp:151842:13"/>his
Aſcenſion; and to the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthieſt, leſs than the leaſt of all, is
this grace given: He hath been pleaſed to open the ſtill Eternity, and to
ſhew the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſſed Deity, in the moſt ſweet harmonious
Stillneſs, deep holy Silence, looking into his own Center of Light, beholding
his own Heart, the lovely Image of Himſelf, which cauſed that Joy and
Deſire of bringing forth his own lovely Image, and this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire brought
forth into manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation the only begotten Son of God, the glorious Image of
the Inviſible God, and the expreſs Character of his Perſon, who is God
bleſſed for evermore; from the Love-Union and Co-Opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God the
Father, and God the Son, did proceed God the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, from the Union and
pure Mingling of the Awful Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtick <pb n="11" facs="tcp:151842:13"/>Light of the
Father, with the Refulgent bright Light of the Son, doth proceed the ſweet
meek peaceful Light of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and theſe Three who bear Witneſs
in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Spirit, agree in One; and all their
Operations are conjunct, as well as diſtinct. As in the Creation and
Producti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the World, the holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son impowered and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated
the bleſſed Spirit, in order to the production of this beautiful World, and
the Spirit of God moved upon the Face of its own Waters, it Self being the
Principle of the Water; the Compariſon of a Hen may not be unfitly uſed,
who firſt produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the Watry ſubſtance of the Egg, and then being
impregna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or filled with Life and Heat, ſhe by moving upon, and hover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151842:14"/>over this moiſt ſubſtance, produceth her own form and
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance: And herein it is that the pure immaculate Virgin Wiſdom, the
holy Spirit of the Eternal God, firſt performs the Office of a Mother, or
Female; from this fruitful Womb it is that all Forms of Things are brought:
<hi>By his Wiſdom he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Earth, and by his Spirit he garniſhed the
Heavens.</hi> Hear what the Voice of our bleſſed Mother Wiſdom ſaith of
this concerning her ſelf, in the Eighth of the <hi>Proverbs;</hi> begin at
the 22th Verſe, and read to the 29th. In the 21th verſe, <hi>When he
prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Heavens, I was there; when he ſet a Compaſs on the Face of
the Depth,</hi> &amp;c. Now as at firſt the World was made by <hi>Ruach
Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him,</hi> the Spirit, Wind, or Breath of God; ſo it is continued by the 
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151842:14"/>ſame Power; if he with-draws his Spirit and his Breath,
we die, and come to nothing; he returns with his Spirit, and renews the face of
all things. Now </p>
            <lg>
               <l>I'll ſing the praiſe of the Eternal One</l>
               <l>I know beſides Him there is none;</l>
               <l>No ſort of Being that can ſay</l>
               <l>It hath its Life another way;</l>
               <l>But from this Deep Abyſſal Ground.</l>
               <l>The Life of all things may be found,</l>
               <l>To Flow out from th' Eternal Source,</l>
               <l>As Springs do from their Water-Courſe.</l>
               <l>Springs may wander, Sheep may ſtray,</l>
               <l>The Sun be clouded at Noon-Day:</l>
               <l>The Shepherd ſeeks the ſtragling Sheep,</l>
               <l>'Tis not the Clouds the Sun can keep</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:151842:15"/>
               <l>From ſhining forth ſo glorious bright,</l>
               <l>As to diſpel their Darkſome Night.</l>
               <l>Great Rivers from the Sea do flow,</l>
               <l>And back into it ſwiftly go:</l>
               <l>So our Great <hi>Alpha</hi>'s <hi>Omega</hi> too;</l>
               <l>Tho' we, like a Bird from her Neſt flew,</l>
               <l>Wander about to find out Reſt,</l>
               <l>We muſt Return ere we are Bleſt:</l>
               <l>And now I am inſpir'd by Thee,</l>
               <l>Bleſt Spirit, I'll praiſe the One, Two, Three.</l>
               <l>For in th' Eternal One doth lie</l>
               <l>The All-Myſterious Trinity.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Oh that Men would praiſe the Lord for his wonderful Works to the
Children of Men! All Creatures ought to praiſe the immenſe Fountain of
their Lives.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:151842:15"/>
            <p>I cannot but put down here a Verſe I read in Dr.
<hi>Ingelo</hi>'s <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivolio.</hi>
            </p>
            <q> 
               <l>We thank thee, God, the Father of us All,</l> 
               <l>And celebrate the Worlds Original.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This is brought to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and I am glad to receive help
through the Veſſel of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to quicken me in this ſweet work of
praiſing God; nay, I ſhould be glad to be ſtirr'd up by the chirping of a
pretty little Bird, who in its kind ſings its Creators Praiſe: But O what
cauſe hath Man to adore and praiſe the great good God, after whoſe Image
he was made, in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs. <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.27. <hi>So
God created Man in his own Image; in the Image of God created he him, Male and
Female <pb n="16" facs="tcp:151842:16"/>created he them:</hi> There is a great Myſtery in
theſe words, which none but the Spirit of God can unfold; not only Man, but
'tis obvious to us, many other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures were thus made, Male and Female; the
very Lights of Heaven are ſo made, as ſaith <hi>Van Helmont,</hi> in a
little Book of his. This I ſay not to ſhew my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; no, I have done
with that vain-glorious Mind; but I am made to value the Teachings of God I
receive from others, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo thoſe which are more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate to my ſelf.
The fiery Male Lights, as the Sun and others, and the cool and watry Lights, as
<hi>Venus</hi> and the <hi>Moon,</hi> with their Female Lights, do by their
va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Motions, Conjunctions, and and the like, perform ſtrange Wonders in
the Heavens above, and in the Earth beneath, by their <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151842:16"/>Influence and Effects; alſo our Terreſtrial Sun and Moon, and
other Watry Lights which inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit our Earth, do alſo perform ſtrange
changes and alterrations in their work-houſe the Caverns of the Earth; and
doubtleſs had Man the Wiſdom reſtored to him which he loſt by the Fall,
could he return to his Paradiſical State, and regain his Empire over the
Creatures, he might with his own hands, (by rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying Agent and
Patient, theſe Fiery Active Lights, and Paſſive Cool Lights, our Sun and
Moon, or our unripe Watry Moon) be enabled to perform Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Effects;
ſuch as might free himſelf and his Fellow-Creatures in a great meaſure
from the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then they groan under; I would not boaſt beyond my line, to
ſay I have done much of this <pb n="18" facs="tcp:151842:17"/>with my own hands; but I
ſee ſomething of it in the Spirit; and if it pleaſe the Great and Good
God, the time may come when I may be enabled to do more, by receiving further
Teachings, either immediately from the Illuminations of his Spirit, or by the
Enlightenings of ſome Perſon ſo Taught: but I find it a hard thing to
come out of the Fallen State, out of the World of Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, out of the
Wiſdom of this World, ſo Purely, ſo Fully, as to be made Fit for the
Bleſſed Teachings and Illuminations of the Spirit of God; though I know the
Wiſdom of this World is Fooliſhneſs with God; yet while any thing remains
of the Fallen Nature, we are apt to be taken with that which we think a Fine
Curious Image in us, or our own Reaſon and Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <pb n="19" facs="tcp:151842:17"/>But this muſt be broken to pieces; for I tell you, ye great Admirers
of Reaſon, ye glory in your ſhame, for it is but the Principle of the
fall'n Nature: 'Tis ſaid, <hi>God breathed into Man the Breath of Life, and
he became a Living Soul:</hi> Man received immediately from God an
Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual Light, and this Light was the Life of Man: <hi>Adam,</hi> while
he ſtood, acted according to, or from this Principle: When the Creatures were
brought before him, he did not enter into the Reaſoning, why this ſhould be
Named ſo, and that otherwiſe; no, from his intellectual Sight and
Knowledge, he ſaw their Natures, and gave them ſuitable Names immediately.
Had Man ſtood, it is plain he had been go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned according to this
Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, by immediate Revelation, <pb n="20" facs="tcp:151842:18"/>and Poſitive
Command, by the Soveraign Will and Wiſdom of his Creator; as appears by the
Command, <hi>And the Lord God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the Man, ſaying, Of every Tree of
the Garden thou mayeſt eat, but of the Tree of the Knowledge of Good and
Evil, thou ſhalt not eat of it;</hi> This Command is poſitive: But Woman,
through the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of the Serpent entred into the Reaſoning, why ſhe
ſhould not eat; <hi>It was pleaſant to the Eyes, and good for Food, and a
Tree to be deſired to make one wiſe;</hi> The why, wherefore, how, and for
what, brought in the deplorable Fall. O how are the Mighty fallen! How are the
Mighty fallen! How is our Gold become Droſs! <hi>God made Man upright, but he
hath ſought out many Inventions; Vain Man would be wiſe, but he is like the
wild Aſſes Colt;</hi> ſnuffing <pb n="21" facs="tcp:151842:18"/>up the Eaſt-Wind of
Vanity and Emptineſs. When Man would remove himſelf from the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate
Conduct of the Wiſdom and Will of God, and would be guided by a Wiſdom and
Will of his own, by his own Reaſon, he broke himſelf off from God; and
inſtead of a Branch of that Noble Vine, he became a dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Plant. And I
tell you, Till we return back by the way we came out of this bleſſed
Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſical State, we cannot be happy; but this is a way the Vultures Eye
hath not ſeen, nor can Reaſon comprehend it; <hi>for the Natural Man
perceiveth not the things of God, neither can he, they are ſpiritually
diſcerned.</hi> But when a Man is brought to ſay, Lord, I feel my ſelf in
a bewil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fall'n ſtate of Darkneſs and the ſhadow of Death; I ſee
thy <pb n="22" facs="tcp:151842:19"/>lovely Image defaced, the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of <hi>David</hi>
fallen to the ground, thy Light in me vailed and covered; I feel my ſelf
bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off from thee my true Root and Original; I would fain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to thee,
but I know not how; Reaſon cannot ſhew me the way. Then the Lord comes and
ſeals Inſtructions, gives his Spirit, enlightens the Man, and tells him,
No, Reaſon cannot ſhew the way to Me; it carried thee off from Me: But come
now, lay down thy own Reaſon, thy own Wiſdom and Will, loſe thy own Life,
that thou may'ſt ſave it; and I will ſhew thee a way my Wiſdom hath
found, which thy Wiſdom or Reaſon could not; for the Wiſdom of this World
is Fooliſhneſs with Me; but I have found out a way will cauſe in thee
Wonder, Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151842:19"/>and Joy. Then the Lord Enlightens our
Minds in the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Scriptures, the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the great work of
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Man by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord his Son, our
Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; the Myſteries which are Revealed in the Sacred
Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture concerning our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, from his Conception to his
Aſcenſion, are ſo Deep and My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterious, that the Plummet Line of
Reaſon cannot fathom them, but they are Revealed to Babes by the ſame
Spirit in which they were written; there is certainly a great Myſtery in the
Conception of our Saviour: The Perſon cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by God to have this Great
Honour of being the Mother of our Lord, was a moſt Excellent Holy Woman and
Pure Virgin; <hi>Mary,</hi> the Eſpouſed VVife of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> but
<hi>Mary</hi> at firſt found <pb n="24" facs="tcp:151842:20"/>difficulty to receive the
Meſſage the Angel brought, this Great and Myſterious Revelation of the
Mind of God concerning her; and She was troubled at his Say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and She caſt
or reaſoned in her mind what manner of Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation this ſhould be; after
the Angel had given her a further account of his Meſſage, which was
wonderful; She again asks, How can this thing be? in <hi>Luke</hi> 1.34. The
Angel Condeſcends to Enlarge and to Diſcover the Myſtery more clearly;
and in v. 35. <hi>And the Angel anſwered, and ſaid unto her, The Holy
Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee, and the Power of the Higheſt ſhall
Overſhadow thee. Therefore alſo that Holy Thing which ſhall be born of
thee, ſhall be called the Son of God.</hi> This anſwer <hi>Mary</hi> could
only receive by Faith and Intellectual Light: And to <pb n="25" facs="tcp:151842:20"/>ſtrengthen her Faith, he further tells her, <hi>With God all things
are poſſible:</hi> What our Belief, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Apoſtles Creed,
ſaith of this Myſtery, is very Excellent, that <hi>he was conceived by the
Power of the holy Ghoſt, in the Womb of the Virgin Mary:</hi> Doubtleſs the
Subſtance of the Virgins own Body was the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer for her being a Virgin, and
a holy Woman, yet it was much purer when the holy Ghoſt came upon her, the
Spirit of the living and Eternal God, the Virgin Wiſdom, the true Virgin
Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, did not, as in the Birth of the World, produce the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance purely
from her ſelf; this would have been Creation; but the holy Ghoſt did
penetrate the Subſtance of the Virgin, and did purify and rariſy it, that
it was a holy Thing indeed that was <pb n="26" facs="tcp:151842:21"/>born of her: It was a
great Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Priviledge the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was made Partaker of; and
doubtleſs a good meaſure of the Spirit of God did abide upon her; but this
power of the Spirit did not reſt upon her, but it did abide upon that holy
thing which was born of her, our bleſſed Lord Jeſus: Now this miraculous
Work, the Conception of our Lord, is the ſecond time the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, the
holy Ghoſt, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Office of a Mother in ſuch an immediate and
extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary manner; and as the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception was wonderful, ſo doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
the Thing conceived was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary; the Body of our Lord was a very pure,
and in a great meaſure a ſpiritual Body; and yet a true Body; for no
Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is the leſs true, but the more ſo, for being Spiritual: The 
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151842:21"/>World, and all things in it, as it came immediately from
the Spirit of God, in its firſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was very good, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore true
and ſubſtantial, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be Good, but what is True: And now I
ſee how Truth, Being, and Goodneſs, are One: Words I have before heard, but
never underſtood till now.</p>
            <p>After the Fall, Man and the whole Creation ſunk more deep into
Materiality, but thereby did not become a more real and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Being,
but a more ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowy one, as it went farther from the Light. Now Matter, when
it is moſt dark, ſhadowy, and at a diſtance, is capable of being reduc'd
to a ſpiritual ſtate, by the Power of God, through the Merits of Chriſt,
by the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of his Spirit; for he <hi>ſhall change our vile Bodies, and
make <pb n="28" facs="tcp:151842:22"/>them like his glorious Body.</hi> Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful changes
do paſs upon Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in this lower World, by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Productions and
Alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and alſo by Artificial ways. As I my ſelf have ſeen and
hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Matter, changed from putri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, vile, ſtinking, to beautiful,
ſweet, and in a degree rarified and refined; and I believe far greater things
of this kind may be performed, than I have yet ſeen. And I know Subſtances
freed, in any degree, from the clogs of Materiality, may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form extraordinary
things. How much more might the Body of our Saviour (that never was ſo
ſtrongly fettered) perform Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, while he was on Earth in the Body, after
his Reſurrection, and now ſince his Aſcenſion, eſpecially being in
all theſe vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtates united to his Divinity: <pb n="29" facs="tcp:151842:22"/>The
Body of our bleſſed Saviour is now in the bleſſed State of
Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification, and I will not diſpute what he can do; but I do not at all
believe he will change this moſt glorious bright ſhining Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of his, into
Fleſh, Blood and Bone, and give it us to eat, and to drink, raw, whole, with
I know not how many Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that ſome profeſt Chriſtians dare to
mention; but I hope this is far from any to believe, there is no need of this;
the Fleſh profits nothing, the Spirit quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens; and except we do eat the
Spiritual Fleſh, and drink the Spiritual Blood of Chriſt, we have no part
in him: Not Fleſh and Blood in a more groſs ſence than our Saviour ever
had to give us, but in ſuch a ſence as a ſpiritual Man by a ſpiritual
Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning may receive; <hi>Lord ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more <pb n="30" facs="tcp:151842:23"/>give me this
Bread;</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly two or three times a year, once a month, or once a week,
or on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in a piece of Bread ſo quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and bleſt, do I deſire it; but
that it may be my daily Food, that I may live upon it: I can no more
ſpiritually live without it a day, than I can live without my daily Bread: I
deſire continually to feed upon the hidden Manna, and to drink the Wine of
the Kingdom, and to feel more of that bleſſed Promiſe made good in me,
that our bleſſed Jeſus gave forth to thoſe that believe on him, That
<hi>out of their Bellies ſhall flow Fountains of Living Waters:</hi> I would
have my ſpiritual Sences always exerciſed about ſpiritual Objects; my Eye
ſtedfaſtly fix'd on my bleſſed Jeſus. Here I muſt ſet down a
Love-Deſire and Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing after Him.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151842:23"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah bleſſed Jeſus! Let me ſee thy Face!</l>
               <l>Let me draw near to thy moſt Holy Place:</l>
               <l>With Wings of Eagles let me mount on High,</l>
               <l>There to behold thy Bright Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</l>
               <l>Tho' I am here encompaſſed with Clay,</l>
               <l>Let me behold the Dawning of thy Day.</l>
               <l>Shine forth, O Lord; from the Center of my Heart</l>
               <l>Let Light Divine fill me in every part.</l>
               <l>O fill my Soul with thy Celeſtial Fire:</l>
               <l>With thy pure Spirit do thou me now inſpire,</l>
               <l>That I may ſing, and bleſs thy Holy Name,</l>
               <l>And may return to thee thy own pure Flame.</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:151842:24"/>
               <l>I will return to thee, my Love, my All;</l>
               <l>Be always ready to obey thy Call.</l>
               <l>Write in my Heart the Royal Law of Love,</l>
               <l>That whilſt Below I may be like thoſe Above;</l>
               <l>Whoſe bleſt Employment is to love and ſing</l>
               <l>Hallelujahs to their Heavenly King.</l>
               <l>Now I will joyn with this moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Quire;</l>
               <l>With them I'll Praiſe, with them I will Admire.</l>
               <l>O Holy, Holy is the Lord! for he</l>
               <l>Gives Life from Death, he ſets the Pris'ner free.</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbind my fetter'd Soul, that it may be</l>
               <l>Above the Earth, and Materia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:151842:24"/>
            <p>Let all the People praiſe thee, O God, let all the People
praiſe thee; thy Saints ſhall bleſs thee. While I have a being, my Soul
ſhall magnify thy Name; thou haſt done for me great things, and that my
Soul knows right well: Tho' I am nothing, nor can do nothing, nor know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but in thee and by thee; I cannot praiſe thee without thee; thou art my Life;
thou haſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten me again to a lively hope; and through the Riches and
free Grace of my God to a poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Creature, a worthleſs Worm, to me is
this Grace given, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Child of God, and to know this third and
laſt Work of the Spirit of God, in perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Office of a Mother, in
making me partaker of the New Birth, and to know what it is to be born again,
not of Water, nor <pb n="34" facs="tcp:151842:25"/>of Blood, but of the Spirit of the living
and true God: Words are empty things, and periſh in their own ſound; but it
is a bleſſed thing to be enabled with the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtles, to ſay,
<hi>What we have ſeen, what our hands have handled, that declare we unto you,
that ye may have Fellowſhip with us; and truly our Fellowſhip is with the
Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and with the Son, through the Holy Spirit.</hi> I tell ye from the
Scriptures of Truth, from my own Experience, from the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Water,
the Blood, and the Spirit, and theſe three agree in one, to bear witneſs on
Earth, That there is no coming to God, nor being Partakers of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption
purchaſed by Jeſus Chriſt, but by the Illumination and Operation of the
Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that the Spirit of God may
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Office of a Holy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther 
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151842:25"/>in us, to bring forth <hi>Jeſus</hi> in Spirit in us,
that Chriſt may be formed in us: The Spirit of God is the
<hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is from Above, that is Free, the Mother of us all,
ſpoken of in the <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations;</hi> this is the <hi>New Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem that
comes down from God out of Heaven, the Bride, the Lambs Wife, that had made her
ſelf rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> When the Spirit of God hath finiſhed the Work upon the
whole Church of God through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, making it appear in the Eye of our Lord in
Beauty, Unity, Purity, then will it be preſented as a Chaſte Virgin to
Jeſus Chriſt. Then ſhe will appear <hi>Fair as the Moon, Clear as the
Sun, Terrible as an Army with Banners.</hi> She will then partake of the
ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celeſtial Sun and Moon, and of the Seven Stars, the Seven Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties
of God. When the <pb n="36" facs="tcp:151842:26"/>Church is thus Beautified and Adorned, our
Lord will ſay, <hi>Ariſe, my Fair One, and come away.</hi> Now this Work
cannot be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in the whole Church, till it is firſt performed in
parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons, by the Uniting of whom, this Work is compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:
Therefore we muſt all look to it, that this Work may be performed in our
ſelves, that the great three-fold Work of the Spirit may be wrought out in
us, the Diſpenſation of the Water, the Blood, and the Fire. Firſt, We
muſt know the Waſhing with pure Water, the Purging our Conſciences from
<hi>dead works, that we may ſerve the living God:</hi> We muſt know alſo
the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Blood <hi>in us,</hi> as well as <hi>for</hi> us, the
ſlaying our own Thoughts and Imaginations; we muſt not ſpare any thing of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151842:26"/>ſelf-hood, not <hi>Agag</hi> and the choiceſt beaſts;
we muſt alſo witneſs the Spirit of Judgment and Burning, the Spirit
ſitting like a Refiners Fire, till at laſt we ſhall find and feel a
Refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Warmth and Heat: a being Baptized with the Holy Ghoſt and with
Fire; this we muſt feel before we can come to dwell with Everlaſting
Burning, <hi>for our God is a Conſuming Fire;</hi> ſhall we ſet the Hay
and Stubble in Battle Array againſt Him, He will paſs through and Burn it,
nothing but what is Pure muſt Remain; if we would dwell in the Holy Hill of
God, and abide in his Tabernacle, we muſt have Clean Hands &amp; Pure Hearts.
The three great Diſpenſations of God with the great World, doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with
the workings of his Spirit in us; the Deluge of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <pb n="38" facs="tcp:151842:27"/>was
the Firſt of theſe, the Apoſtle ſpeaking of it, ſaith, <hi>The like
figure whereunto is Baptiſm, not only outward Baptiſm with water which
taketh away the filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Fleſh:</hi> but it ſignifies the being
Baptized into Chriſt, into his Death and Sufferings, that being Buryed with
him in Baptiſm, being Dead with Chriſt we alſo may Ariſe with him, and
know the Power of his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, that we being Riſen with Chriſt, may
ſeek thoſe things which are Above, where Chriſt is at the right hand of
God: The Second Great Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation with the Great World was, The Slaying
of Beaſts, the Shedding of Blood, without which there is no Remiſſion;
but this was not only the Blood of Bulls and Goats, that would not do; for the
Law is but a <pb n="39" facs="tcp:151842:27"/>Shadow of Good Things to come; for it is
impoſſible that the Blood of Bulls and Goats ſhould take away Sins; but
this great work was done by the Shedding the Precious Blood of Chriſt; the
Firſt was done away, that he might eſtabliſh the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond; the Sacrifice
of the Law, could not make the comers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto Perfect, but Chriſt by one
Offering hath Perfected for ever them that are Sanctified; by the will of God
we are Sanctified, thorough the Offering of the Body of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and
thoſe that are Members of his Body, muſt alſo be Perfected through
Sufferings, when we come to know what it is to have the word of God Quick and
Powerful in us, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding between the Marrow and the Bone, we ſhall know what
this means; there will be Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <pb n="40" facs="tcp:151842:28"/>off Right Hands,
Plucking out Right Eyes, Slaying and Crucifying the Old Man, with the Affection
and Luſts; This is hard work: Ah my God! let me give up all to it, I would
not ſpare any thing in me; let this work go on in me to the making an end of
Sin, and the Finiſhing tranſgreſſion, that every thought may be brought
into Subjection to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who I would have to Rule and
Reign till all his Enemies are brought under: I Bleſs and Praiſe thy Great
and Glorious Name O Lord my God, for what thou haſt done for me and in me; I
Bow before Thee, and Adore him that Sits upon the Throne, and the Lamb that was
Slain, who was Dead and is Alive, and Lives and Reigns for Ever. The Third and
Laſt Great and Univerſal Diſpenſation <pb n="41" facs="tcp:151842:28"/>of God with
the Great World, will be the Fiery Tryal, when the Elements ſhall Melt with
Fervent Heat, and the Earth and all things in it that is Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtible,
ſhall be Burnt up; that which is Pure will Remain, when the Goldſmith puts
the Droſſy Gold into the Fire, ſome that may not know the nature of it,
may wonder that he ſhould burn his Gold, but he knows though the Droſs will
be burnt, the Gold will remain and come forth more bright; ſo will it be with
the works of God, not only his Throne, but that which now is his Foot-ſtool,
ſhall be Pure Gold, Clear as Chryſtal; he that reads let him underſtand
what the Spirit ſaith. But our great Work is to Cry to the Lord, that the
Fiery Work of his Spirit may paſs upon us, before this <pb n="42" facs="tcp:151842:29"/>great and terrible day of the Lord come; for this Day will try eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
Mans Work, of what ſort it is; and the Hay and Stubble muſt be burnt up,
when our Lord ſhall appear in Flames of Fire, to render Vengeance on all
thoſe that know him not, and obey not the Goſpel. To fit us for this great
Day, the Lord ſends his Spirit of Judgment and Burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into us; and this Day
of the Lord burns like an Oven; his Eyes are a Flame of Fire, who looks into
us; and we are all naked and bare before the Eyes of him with whom we have to
do: Let us not like <hi>Adam</hi> hide our ſelves, but cry out, <hi>Search me
and try me, O God.</hi> Let us with <hi>Moſes</hi> enter into the
Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Fire; God is in the Fire, and tho' it may be terrible,
ſhrink not at it, and endure, as ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151842:29"/>him that is
inviſible, who will appear to be with thee in it, as with the Three Children
in the fiery Furnace, when thou art brought to endure, as they did.
<hi>Elijah</hi> was able to endure the fiery Chariot, having been filled with
the Spirit of the Lord, that pure fiery Spirit had Tinctured him throughout,
and made him able to endure the fire. Ah my God, I am now in thy Furnace, and
have been ſome time: Let me not think it ſtrange concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fiery
Trial, as if ſome ſtrange thing happened to me; make me to endure the time
and degree of heat thou ſeeſt beſt for me: I would be Gold ſeven times
refined; this I know cannot be done, without entering into the Furnace again
and again: Lord continue this Work, till thou haſt finiſhed Sin, and made
an end of <pb n="44" facs="tcp:151842:30"/>Tranſgreſſion: Purge me, that I may bring
forth more Fruit, Fruits of Righteouſneſs, Fruits of Renown, that there may
be Plants in me of thy own Right Hand Planting, that I may be ready to every
good Word and Work. This do thou do for me, and do not forſake me.</p>
            <lg>
               <head>A Breathing after the holy Spirit of God.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spring up, O Well, now ſpring in me,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Let me Refreſhed by thy Waters be.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I feel thy Holy Quickning Breath,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which brings me from the Gates of Death:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy Wind blows freely, thy Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter's ſweet;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Power of thy Flames are great.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:151842:30"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy Breath, thy Fire, thy Water-Spring.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is the Life, the Birth of every thing:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Outward and Inward, both do grow</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>y thy Pure Water's Over-flow.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If thou with draw'ſt thy Quickning Breath,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>There's nought remains in me but Death.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Do thou with Fire me now baptize,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That I may be a whole Burnt Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And into Aſhes I would turn,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If thou, O Lord, wouldſt be my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rn.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>Glory be to the Father, and to the Son, by the holy Spirit, now
and for ever. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Some may ask me, What Right haſt thou to Worſhip be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the
Altar, to ſpeak or write <pb n="46" facs="tcp:151842:31"/>of Divine Things? Thou art not
qualified with Learning, and Ordination of ſome great learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man. I ſay,
'Tis true, I am neither Prophet, nor Prophets Son, in this ſence; I am not of
the Aaronical or Levitical Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, nor capable of it: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, my God
hath made me a King and a Prieſt to him, in ſome degree; and I doubt not,
but in my bleſſed Jeſus, by his Spirit, I may offer ſome acceptable
Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; <hi>The Sacrifice of a broken and a contrite Heart, thou wilt not
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, O my God.</hi> My bleſſed and glorious <hi>Jeſus,</hi> was
not a Prieſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Order of the <hi>Aaronical</hi> and
<hi>Levitical</hi> Prieſthood, but after the Order of <hi>Melchizedeck,</hi>
who was Prieſt of the moſt high God, to whom <hi>Aaron</hi> paid Tythes in
the Loyns of his Father <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> And this <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> was 
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:151842:31"/>King of Righteouſneſs, King of Peace; 'tis an excellent
intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to the Prieſthood, to be made ſo within our Selves; this
Temper of Mind, doth not only introduce, but always ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the True
Prieſthood, who are made Prieſts unto God by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our
Saviour, who was made a Prieſt after the Order of Melchiſedeck, and bore a
reſemblance with him as he was without Father and without Mother. Which
words, wherein <hi>Melchizedeck</hi> was a type of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I have
not upon me to explain as it relates to our Saviour; but in this ſence, as it
reſpects my Self, I am without Father, to appoint me to the Prieſthood, I
mean without Man to do this; without Mother, as any Viſible Church (for ought
I know) that will own me; yet I am not very <pb n="48" facs="tcp:151842:32"/>ſolicitous
for this, if I may be of the Church of the Firſt Born, whoſe Names are
written in Heaven; I would act as a Free-Deniſon of this City, who is my True
Mother; I would act by that Free Spirit that Teaches and Guides her Children.
And it is a Promiſe to her, that all her Children ſhall be Taught of God,
and Great ſhall be the Peace of her Children. O my God, do thou thus Guide me
and Teach me, that being Born of the Spirit, I may be led by the Spirit, and
know the Truth as it is in <hi>Jeſus;</hi> though I am in a Wilderneſs,
full of Difficulties, let me not be without a Guide; if Thou leaveſt me a
moment, I Slip, I Fall. I find the way Strait; the farther I go in it, the more
Strait, but alſo Pleaſant; I can Truly, Feelingly ſay, Lord, 
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:151842:32"/>
               <hi>All thy ways are pleaſantneſs, and all thy paths
are peace.</hi> I would not wander about to change my way: do Thou help me to
make ſtrait ſteps to my feet; help me to Travel onward through all
Difficulties, having my Loyns girt, my Lamp trimmed, ready to meet my Lord, in
that City of Solemnities where I would always Praiſe thee, always A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore
thee, always Love thee, Thou Great God of Sabbaths for ever.</p>
            <p>Some may ſay, they fear I do not enough Value Ordianances, I
ſeem ſo indifferent about Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination: I ſay, the Spirit of the Prophets,
are ſubject to the Prophets; there are Babes in Chriſt, there are alſo
Young Men and Fathers or Elders, ſuch whoſe Age, Long Experience in the
things of God, being filled <pb n="50" facs="tcp:151842:33"/>with the Spirit of Wiſdom,
Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and a Sound Mind, makes them very Venerable; ſuch who have
known him that is from the Begining, who have the Spirit of the Holy God living
in them, who can Unfold Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Reveal Secrets; ſuch who not only
Speak, but by the Power of God are Enabled to Effect ſomething in the minds
of Men, to convey of the ſame Spirit they have Received. It is a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural
Maxim, <hi>Every Like produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth its Like:</hi> It is true in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual
Things, the Apoſtles and Prophets had this Power, and I doubt not but there
are ſome have the ſame Qualifications now; ſuch indeed who feel
themſelves empty of ſuch Power and Vertue, are ready to doubt of this, and
poſitively ſometimes to ſay, theſe Things are Ceaſed, 
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:151842:33"/>we muſt not expect them now; this apprehenſion of
theirs muſt needs hinder their receiving this Great Bleſſing; and I know
no ground they have for it from Scripture; our Saviour tells his People, He
will be with them always to the end of the World; He promiſed the Spirit to
Teach them, to Guide them, to Aſſiſt them to do Great and Mighty Works;
our Saviour no where ſays, he will take away this Bleſſing again; the
Prophets had the Spirit in an extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry manner under the Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of the Law, they performed Wonders, they had Servants, and ſuch as were
called Sons of the Prophets under their Tuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, whom they Inſtructed in the
Sacred Myſteries, to whom they conveyed much of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as
<hi>Elijah</hi> to <hi>Eliſha,</hi> by caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="52" facs="tcp:151842:34"/>his
Mantle upon him: let not the pretenſions of any (in our time) to this, who
have not been real Poſſeſſors of it, make us doubt the thing, no more
then we doubt of the Truth of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, becauſe we ſee ſo
many who in Words Profeſs Chriſt, but in Works Deny him. This is a certain
ſign of a True Prophet, He is one who fears God, hates Covetouſneſs; he
Feeds the People with Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Underſtanding; the Love of Money is the
root of all Evil: now let all Chriſtians, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially ſuch as profeſs
to be Prophets, deſire that the Ax may be laid to this Root of the Tree; I
greatly Value the Sage Advice, Counſel, Bleſſing of ſuch a Perſon; I
expect their Bleſſing ſhould convey fome real Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage as the
Patriarchs of old did; <pb n="53" facs="tcp:151842:34"/>if ſuch ſhould deliver a
Perſon up to Satan, he may expect to feel the Effects of it; but when
Sentence is pronounced by ſuch as have Word without Power, upon a miſtaken
ground; a Perſon againſt whom ſuch a Sentence is pronounced, feels not
the ſad Effect, but it may be the contrary, more of the Spirit of God then
ever. But if I am o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertaken with a fault, I hope one that is Spiritual may
Reſtore me again in the Spirit of Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; if a Spiritual Man who hath a
Diſcerning, deſire me to Speak or Write, it hath a great Authority with me;
if ſuch an one ſay to me forbear, it hath great Power; however I have not
Conſulted any in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of theſe Writings, nor had either Counſel
or Aſſiſtance of any Man, yet when I have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <pb n="54" facs="tcp:151842:35"/>I
ſubmit them to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch; if ſuch a one gives me a piece of
Bread, a Cup of Wine, or of Cold Water, I believe he will have a Diſciples
Reward, and I a Diſciples Bleſſing; if ſuch an one goes about to
inſtruct me in Sacred Myſteries, I hearken with great Attention, knowing he
hath a deep ſight into the Wonders of God manifeſted in the Creatures, for
by the things that are made, are ſeen his Eternal Power and Godhead.</p>
            <p>Such Perſons live not in this World, ſo full of Wiſdom and
Beauty, only to look on the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides of things, and only to reaſon about
them; why this is ſo, and that ſo; this Hot and that Cold, only for
Diſcourſe ſake; no, they Live in the World as Prieſts in a Temple, and
Praiſe God for <pb n="55" facs="tcp:151842:35"/>the things that are, as <hi>Hermes</hi>
ſpeaks; they have an Eye opened by the Spirit of God, by which they have an
Intellectual Sight into the Creatures; and thereby have a power given alſo to
alter and change them, and to turn their Inſides Out; to make the Light which
was hid in the Center, appear through its out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Shell, the dark Vail and
Shadowy Covering, it hath upon it; and thereby regain the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Authority
Man had given him at firſt of Subjecting the Creatures to his Rule, and
making them ſerve his Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; tho at preſent, Perſons thus
Highly Endowed with Wiſdom Divine &amp; Natural (if I may uſe that
diſtinction at all, both com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from one root) are obſcure and not much
known in the World; yet I firmly believe <pb n="56" facs="tcp:151842:36"/>the time is very
near, when the World ſhall be Bleſt with the knowledge of their Perſons,
and the opening the Treaſures Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath furniſhed them with: Now to
the Honourable Fathers and Worthy Brothers of this Happy Society, who are thus
Led and Taught, wherever you are through the whole World, I ſend greeting;
you are all my Fathers, you are all my Maſters and Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, particularly my
Maſter <hi>T. S.</hi> I humbly deſire to be received by you as a Pupil, as
a Servant to Waſh your feet: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſuffer this Word of Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
from me at preſent; let us all <hi>ſing the Hymn of Silence</hi> within our
ſelves, till we are permitted to utter the Praiſe of the Great
<hi>Jehovah</hi> in the Great Congregation, ſo that our Voice may be heard
through the whole <pb n="57" facs="tcp:151842:36"/>earth, for the whole World is our Temple,
our Church; and we deſire to joyn with every Creature, things in Heaven,
things on Earth, and under the Earth, to praiſe the All-glorious GOD that
created all things; by whom and through whom are all things. To whom be all
Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, World without End. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>My Soul ſhall ſing Jehovah's Praiſe;</l>
               <l>Let that Great Name my Spirit raiſe;</l>
               <l>That I may with the Angels joyn,</l>
               <l>To ſing a Hymn that is Divine.</l>
               <l>That I may reach the Seraphick Quire,</l>
               <l>Being quickned with the ſame pure Fire</l>
               <l>That makes them ſing, and makes them love,</l>
               <l>In their Harmonious Orbs above.</l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:151842:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:151842:37"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:151842:38"/>
               <l>Let ſuch high Praiſe in Heaven abound,</l>
               <l>May make Earth eccho to the ſound;</l>
               <l>That all the Creatures her below,</l>
               <l>The Mighty Power of Love may know.</l>
               <l>Good Will to Man ſo doth appear,</l>
               <l>As makes him know his GOD is near,</l>
               <l>To ſave poor Mankind'd fallen Race,</l>
               <l>And bring him to his Native Place.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:151842:38"/>
            <head>The Second Part.</head>
            <head>SOME Diſcoveries of the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the
Six Days Work, and the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Days Reſt.</head>
            <p>O Eternal Father of Life and Power, how ſweet a Sabbath haſt
thou made this to me, in giving my Soul Reſt and Repoſe in thy ſelf!
Bleſſed God of Sabaoth! I find Reſt in thee is ſweet, ſince thou
haſt made that bleſſed Promiſe <pb n="60" facs="tcp:151842:39"/>good, to ſuch as
are weary and heavy laden, that in coming to thee they find reſt to their
Souls. Dear and bleſſed JESUS! thou Shepherd and Biſhop of my Soul, lead
me in thy green Paſtures, by the ſtill Waters of Quietneſs, till thou
doſt make me to know where thou makeſt thy Flocks to reſt at Noon; that
the hotteſt Affliction, the moſt fiery Tryal, may not interrupt my ſweet
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in thee: Let me no more ſeek Reſt and Satisfaction in the
Creature, where it is not to be had; let me no more ſeek the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
amongſt the Dead, but as the World is crucified unto me, let me be crucified
unto the World. Lord help me to dye daily, to live continually in holy
Reſignation, that when thou ſhalt call me to lay down this houſe of Clay,
this Earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151842:39"/>I may be enabled to ſay with my
bleſſed Saviour, <hi>No man takes away my Life;</hi> if it is by the hand
of Man, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever other way, I may freely lay down my Life, and be willing
to be Uncloathed, that I may be Cloathed upon with my Houſe from Heaven, that
being Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed upon, I may not be found Naked; but may be ready to enter into
the Reſt that remains for the People of God; into that good Land, the
heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> where ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away, where
I may ſing the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> and of the Lamb, who is worthy of
Praiſe and Adoration for ever.</p>
            <p>The 29th of <hi>July</hi> 1688. I may ſay with the holy St.
<hi>John, I was in the Spirit on the Sabbath Day, on the Lords Day;</hi> &amp;
he was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <pb n="62" facs="tcp:151842:40"/>to ſhow me, as before I had ſeen, how
Stillneſs and Reſt is the true ground of Motion, in God himſelf, and of
all true, good, regular Motion of the Creature, ſo all ſuch Motion is in
order to Reſt: God himſelf, after the ſix Days Work, reſted on the
Seventh Day; ſo the Lord bleſſed the Seventh Day. And it is a bleſſed
thing indeed, when we come in any degree to this perfect Number Seven: The
Number of the Beaſt is Six hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Sixty Six; and if you add more Sixes, it
is but the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Beaſt, or at moſt but the Number of a Man, it
cannot be a perfect Number; no, it is the Number Seven is the perfect Number,
when we come to know in our own Souls the ſweet Reſt, to reſt from our
Labours, as God did from his, when we die <pb n="63" facs="tcp:151842:40"/>in the Lord, and
reſt from our Labours, and our Works do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low us. He that can underſtand,
let him underſtand. This 30th of <hi>July</hi> the ſweet Teachings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide
upon me, and I muſt follow my Guide, who now ſhews me ſomething of the
Six Days work, in opening the Firſt Chapter of <hi>Geneſis</hi> to me,
thus: <hi>In the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, In principio,</hi> in the beginning or firſt
Manifeſtation of this Principle, <hi>Elohim</hi> the Mighty God of Power,
<hi>Created,</hi> made out of Nothing, ſome ſay: I know not what Nothing
their Imaginations frame to them; but I am ſure, when about Seventeen or
Eighteen years of Age, I look'd into their Expoſitions, Annotations,
Commentaries, all I could find, no other account was given; but <hi>made out of
No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> which left me not at all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied; <pb n="64" facs="tcp:151842:41"/>but
the Lord is pleaſed to open to me one Scripture by another, <hi>The things
that are made are not made of things that do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear;</hi> they are made of
Nothing that does appear, but of Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that doth not appear, <hi>viz.</hi>
of that which is inviſible. In the beginning, God made, created, produced the
Heavens and the Earth; the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of which both were formed,
but the Earth was then without Form, and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was upon the Face of the
Deep: Some repreſent this Chaos methinks but oddly, call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it <hi>rude
Chaos,</hi> where all things lay, they ſay, confuſed: I will not cavil
about Words, but this gives a ſtrange Repreſentation of this Principle, out
of which ſuch a beautiful and orderly World was produced. Now to me, this
very Chaos hath a Beauty in it: <pb n="65" facs="tcp:151842:41"/>I cannot but ſay, O
beautiful Darkneſs! O holy Night! The Mother of all things! In this dark
Chariot doth the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Creator, the Great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> ride forth
magnificently; and when the Vail was drawn away, the Light appear'd; <hi>And
God ſaid, Let there be Light, and there was Light:</hi> This Light was
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hid in the Darkneſs, till it it was manifeſted at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of
God; the Light was mingled with the Darkneſs in the Chaos, and innumerable
o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſeeming Contrarieties; but not confuſed, none of God's Creatures can
be ſo; for God is a God of Order, not of Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; his Works are
performed with the ſwift motion, agility, powerful operation of a moſt
glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Spirit; and alſo as a wiſe Architect with order, weight and 
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:151842:42"/>ſure proportionates all things, and made the lower Orders
of things anſwer to their Patterns in the Heavenly: A man doth not make any
thing but what hath ſome ſort of ſpiritual exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in his Mind,
before it can be produc'd into Out-working with his hands: Infinitely,
tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently more hath all things ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially, really a being in
the Eternal Idea's in the Divine Mind. Man hath power over the Creatures, to
change and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Subſtance, but he hath not power to make the
ſubſtance, not the leaſt part of it, but God produceth the ſubſtance
&amp; form, and all from himſelf: The Light of this Creation is a Reflexion
of the Superceleſtial Light. <hi>And God ſaw the Light that it was good,
and God divided the Light from the Darkneſs; and God called 
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:151842:42"/>the Light Day, and the Darkneſs he called Night; and the
Evening and the Morning were the firſt Day.</hi> When the Light was
ſeparated from the Darkneſs, and brought forth into a diſtinct
Exiſtence, this was the end of the Firſt Day's Work: There is a
Philoſophical Work which is an Excellent Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure of this Firſt Days Work;
When an enlightned Man, a wiſe Man, takes ſome part of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, of
the Subſtance or Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and cauſeth it to paſs into Death and
Putrifaction, it comes to be like the Chaos, of which it was once a part, it
goes into a ſtate of Darkneſs and Blackneſs; but the wiſe Man is not
frighted at this ſight, but knows this doth neceſſarily precede the
Light, and that it doth include the Light; and if he continues his Operation,
he knows he ſhall certainly ſee a <pb n="68" facs="tcp:151842:43"/>bright white Light
appear, and there will be a ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween this Light and Darkneſs,
which is an end of his firſt Days Work. This alſo is a Figure of the New
Creation, which God works in bringing Man to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf out of the fallen
ſtate, which is done by bringing Man to a ſtate of Dying; he muſt be
brought to a ſtate of Contrition, Crucifixion, a ſpiritual Dying with
Chriſt, Dying to Sin, Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Self; now this is a ſtate of Darkneſs and
of the Shadow of Death indeed: But the Spirit of God moves upon theſe dark
Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, upon this Deep, and cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the Light to appear, he illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates
the Man, cauſeth the Light to ſhine out of Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecurity; for this Light is
in the Darkneſs, though the Darkneſs comprehendeth it not: Now this 
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:151842:43"/>Enlightning, this ſeparation of the Light from the
Darkneſs, is the Firſt Day's Work of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God in the Minds of
Men. Thus there is an Excellent Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Harmony in all the Works and
Ways of God. Let none think it ſtrange, that I make uſe of Natural and
Artificial things, to explain Divine: Our Lord Jeſus made uſe not only of
Natural Productions, but of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Employments, as Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phors; he mentions
the Sower of Seed, the Vine-Dreſſer, the Woman's hiding her Leaven in three
Meaſures of Meal till all is leavened. This laſt Parable hath an excellent
Significancy in it of things Divine, Natural, and Philoſophical, or
Artificial; but it is now, as it was then, to ſome it is given to know the
Myſteries of the Kingdom, to others it is <pb n="70" facs="tcp:151842:44"/>not given. But
there are ſome now who think ſo high of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that it is below
them to look into the Creatures; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Great and Mighty
<hi>Jehovah</hi> did condeſcend to make them, and doth preſerve them every
moment; and takes ſuch care, that the meaneſt of them falls not to the
ground without the Will of our heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father.</p>
            <p>I am now to ſay ſomething of the Second Day's Work of
Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation. <hi>And God ſaid, Let there be a Firmament in the midſt of the
Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and let it divide the Waters from the Waters; and God made the
Firmament, and divided the Waters which were under the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, from the
Waters which were above the Firmament, and it was ſo; and God called the
Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Heaven: And the Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="71" facs="tcp:151842:44"/>and the Morning were
the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the Light was ſeparated from the Darkneſs, in the
Firſt Day's Work, the Second Day the Light was Rarified and Expand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it was
extended or ſpread forth to a wonderful Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and ſo it became
the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, which God called Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. It is ſaid, <hi>The Lord
ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out the Heavens as a Curtain, as a Tent to dwell in:</hi> Thus as
a wiſe Builder, a curious Architect, the Lord covers the top of the
Stru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture before he finiſheth the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious In works: The Chaos was a Watry
Subſtance, an Unctuous Humidity, the Principle of the Water was predominant;
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scripture here calls it <hi>Water,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The Spirit
of God moved upon the face of the Waters.</hi> Fire and Water are the two
moſt <pb n="72" facs="tcp:151842:45"/>ſubſtantial Principles, Earth and Air are
produced from them; Water is the Root and Begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Fire the Perfection and
End of all things. The Unctuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Oylineſs of the Chaos, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd
the Light, or rather was the Light and Fire; the Water was in this beginning of
things the greateſt quantity, till the Fire gets the Predominancy; the
Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, the Light and Heat di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided the Waters from the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; thus a
vaſt quantity of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters was moſt wiſely placed, part of it below the
Fire, that its piercing ſubſtance might not with its fiery heat penetrate
the Earth too ſwiftly with its quick motion, till the Earth was brought more
towards a ſtate of Perfection; the Firmament was placed between the Waters to
Concoct and Ripen them, and to <pb n="73" facs="tcp:151842:45"/>bring their Watry into a
Fiery Subſtance; the Oleous Quality of the Chaos was Fire, but when it was
expanded into the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it much loſt its force, and became more
properly Light and Heat, than Fire, as it is now placed; ſo that we here
ſee the meaning of that word, <hi>The Voice of the Lord divideth the Flames
of Fire;</hi> the moſt compact Body of Fire is divided till it comes to be
hardly any longer Fire: Bodies are diviſible, Spirits not; the nearer any
Body is to Spirit, the more hard to have its parts divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: Fire is that
wonderful Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, I muſt not, I dare not at this time ſay any more of
the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it. But notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fire is brought into this
peaceful Temperature, in the making the Firmament, yet it retains ſo much the
Nature of <pb n="74" facs="tcp:151842:46"/>Fire, that if it is agitated and contracted, it
becomes Fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; as we ſee by a common Experiment, it is done by the
Burning-Glaſs: But it is made out Excellently and Clearly, by the account we
have of the Laſt Great Conflagration; in the Scriptures it is ſaid, <hi>The
Element ſhall melt with fervent heat;</hi> and that it ſhall be <hi>wrapped
up like a Scroul;</hi> which paſſage explains the former; its being wrapped
up, contracted, and brought into a narrower compaſs, will ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe
the intenſe heat, that <hi>the Element ſhall melt, and the Earth and all
things in it ſhall be burnt up.</hi> And thus it is ſhewed mo the
Conflagration, burning the Earth by Fire, ſhall in ſome reſpects
reſemble the Deluge by Water; then the <hi>Windows of Heaven were opened, and
the Fountains of the <pb n="75" facs="tcp:151842:46"/>great Deeps were broken up:</hi> So in
the Diſpenſation of Fire, the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall perform its Office of
Burning, as hath been a little before deſcribed; alſo the impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned
Fires in the Powels of the Earth, ſhall be ſet at liberty; their Deep
ſhall be broken up, that they may meet their beloved up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Flames, to which
they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways tend. And it appears to me, that as the World grows nearer its
period, nearer this Diſpenſation of Fire, the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral Fires do more break
their Priſons, make their way out of the Earth, gain Victory over the Waters
under the Earth, and ſometimes above the Surface of the Earth; as is ſeen
by <hi>Veſuvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Aetna,</hi> and other Burnings, that in our time have
wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully iſſued forth, and ſhewed their Conqueſt over the Water, 
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151842:47"/>by ſad Effects: And Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes may be ſometimes
cauſed by the ſtrife of Fire and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which when Fire gets the
predominancy, cauſes the Earth to open; for we commonly ſee the exceſs of
Drineſs makes the Earth chap and gape, Moiſture makes it more continuous,
or clinging together.</p>
            <p>Now I cannot but return with Admiration to behold the Beauty and
Wiſdom of this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Day's Work, and ſay, <hi>tIt was very good: And the
Evening and the Morning was the Second Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O Admirable Order of things! How am I raviſhed with the ſight!
Who can enter into the deep of this one Sentence, <hi>The Evening and the
Morning was the Second Day!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:151842:47"/>
            <p>According to my ſcanty mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I ſhall deſcribe the
Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers Second Day's Work. It is not to be wondred if I do it not ſo
exactly as ſome others, who have more of the Spirit of Wiſdom, and are
Poſſeſſors of her Treaſures, while I profeſs to be only a Seeker
and Lover: It appears to me that the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers Firmament is ſpread out
like a Molten Looking-Glaſs; and to me none but a wiſe Man can well
underſtand this Paſſage, he hath ſeen his Light ariſe out of the
Darkneſs, and expatiate it ſelf to the filling his Recipient, how large
ſoever it be, his Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament is Light, hath the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Fire in it, which
is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed with Water above, and underneath the Water is predominant;
in the beginning of his Work is the greateſt quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151842:48"/>that he is ready to call it Superfluous Humidity; but as his Work
grows towards a ſtate of Perfection, the Fire prevails, it becomes a Child of
the Fire, lives in the Fire, feeds on the Fire; I mean not Devouring Fire; this
appears not to be in it, unleſs it is agitated and ſtirred up by too
violent motion: But Light or Fire ſo mingled by gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle procedure, with the
Water that it partakes of, the Meek Peaceful Nature of the Water, and gives
forth ſo much of its own permanent compact Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that they become one
excellently qualified Eſſence, Fire being in this ſtate of Perfection
predominant; but ſuch a Fire as is before deſcribed, that doth not
deſtroy, but exalt the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to a more fix'd, pure, perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
ſtate: I ſay ſomething of <pb n="79" facs="tcp:151842:48"/>this Work, as it is at the
conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in this Second Day's Work, becauſe Light and Heat, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the
Firmament conſiſts, are powerful Agents to begin and end the Work withal:
But the ſpreading forth the Light into a Beautiful Mirror, is the end of his
Second Day's Work.</p>
            <p>Now there is an admirable Teaching in this, it is a Figure of the
Work of the Spirit of God in illuminating the Minds of Men; which is a
Tranſlating them out of the Kingdom of Darkneſs, into the Kingdom of the
dear Son of God: This is done in ſome meaſure in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, in the
firſt Day's Work, but is greatly increaſed in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, till we are
brought into his Marvellous Light. When the Light Center is open in us, which
was ſhut and vailed in the Fall, it <pb n="80" facs="tcp:151842:49"/>is a bleſſed
thing; but when it ſpreads it ſelf, that the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding is
enlightened in the Knowledge of God, of himſelf, and in ſome degree of the
Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion round about him, he comes again to be but a little lower than the
Angels, who are Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligences, who are Fire; <hi>He ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his Angels
Spirits, and thoſe Miniſters of his Flames of Fire:</hi> Nay, Man in his
firſt Creation was an Excellently Noble Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he was the Epitomy of the
whole World; he was the Little World, in which the Great was compriſed; he
had the Elements and all Creatures within himſelf. We may well ſay, <hi>We
are fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and wonderfully made,</hi> with holy <hi>David,</hi> who had his
Eyes opened to ſee his own Excellent Make. But if the firſt Creation was
glorious, how much more <pb n="81" facs="tcp:151842:49"/>is the Second, the New Creation in
Man, <hi>when old things ſhall paſs away, and all things become new?</hi>
And one admirable part of this Work, is the bringing forth the New Heaven in
us, the New Firmament, wherein is Light, Serenity, Calmneſs; the Fire being
tempered with the meek Waters of Quietneſs, ſo that the wrathful property
of the Fire, is changed into a ſweet peaceful Light; but this Light Centre
cannot be opened in us, but by our bleſſed JESUS, who <hi>hath the Key of
David, who opens and no Man ſhuts; and ſhuts, and no Man opens:</hi> O!
'tis our bleſſed JESUS, who opens his own Light in us by his Spirit; he
cauſeth his glorious Light to ſhine out of the Darkneſs, and to ariſe,
and to enlarge it ſelf, till our whole Body is full of <pb n="82" facs="tcp:151842:50"/>Light: There is a certain ſign given, to know whether the whole Body
is full of Light; <hi>If thy Eye is ſingle,</hi> our dear Lord tells us,
<hi>our whole Body is full of Light:</hi> The ſingle Eye is, when we fix our
Eye upon the Light, on the Good, firſt in God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and in all the
Creatures where it is ſcattered up and down, but all from the ſame Root.
Now God himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds the Evil and the Good, but he dwells in the Light:
So, tho' we may ſee the Evil, we muſt ſhut our Eye to it, and open it to
the Good; thus ſtedfaſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Light, we ſhall be transformed
into its Likeneſs. However, every thing is beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in its Seaſon:
<hi>The Evening as well as the Morning is the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="83" facs="tcp:151842:50"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And God ſaid again, Let the Waters under the Heaven be
ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together into one place, and let the dry Land appear; and it was
ſo: Then God ſaid, Let the Earth bring forth the Bud of the Herb that
ſeedeth Seed, the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Tree that beareth Fruit,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and it
was ſo. And God ſaw that it was good: And the Evening and the Morning were
the Third Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this Third Day's Work, there was a gathering together of vaſt
quantities of Waters that made the Seas, thoſe mighty Oceans, where the
Wonders of God are ſeen by thoſe who go down into the Deep in Ships. Surely
the Waters were at firſt the greateſt part of this Globe of the lower
World: They yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main very great, tho' more Ground hath been gain'd ſince
the firſt Creation, as is plain in <pb n="84" facs="tcp:151842:51"/>many parts of the
World. There remains in the Sea ſuch a quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Oleous Light, or
fiery part of the Chaos, as ripens them, and ſometimes gains ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and
a little dries them up, and leſſens their Quantity. This Subſtance when
it is agira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, makes the Sea boil like a Pot; it often appears like Fire: And
who know the Nature of Salt, eſpecially Sea-Salt, will know that this is
ſo; and they will know the meaning of that word, <hi>Every Sacrifice ſhall
be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned with Fire, and ſalted with Salt,</hi> which are equivalent
terms. Now in the ſeparation of the Elements, when the Light was carried
upwards, and much Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with it, and the Waters were gathered together in this
Globe, the dry Land appeared; the Light and Waters being ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151842:51"/>from it, the Earth appear'd but a <hi>Caput Mortuum,</hi> a
Dead Earth, till the Prolifick Virtue was call'd forth by the Word of God; and
then it appeared that Heaven had not left the Earth, without firſt imprinting
alovely Image upon it: There was left in it ſo much Life and Heat as quickned
it to bring forth innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable Vegetable Subſtances of various Size, Shape,
Colour; Fruits, and Herbs, and Flowers, with great Variety of Taſte, and
Fragrancy of Smell; all to ſhew forth the Bounty and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of our
Great Creator: How freely did the Teeming Earth, in this Virgin-ſtate of
Purity, bring forth the various beautiful Forms of Vegetable Subſtances,
before it was Clogg'd and Burthen'd with the Curſe? The Earth we tread on, as
Contemptible as we <pb n="86" facs="tcp:151842:52"/>are apt to think of it,
notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Diſadvantage it hath by the Fall of Man, which brought
the Curſe upon it, there is that Luſtre, Beauty, Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in it, that if
the ſame Spirit that made it, pleaſe to open our Eyes to ſee, we ſhall
behold with wonder. Sure ſuch Wiſdom is worth our ſeeking and praying
for, which we have great Encon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to do, when we read of the great
Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who knew the Nature of all Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, from the
Tall Cedar, to the Low but Sweet Hyſſop: The reſidue of the Spirit is
with the Lord, but for theſe things he will be ſought unto; and they that
ſeek, ſhall find a meaſure of Wiſdom, if not ſo great: But we muſt
dig deep for it, as for hid Treaſures, and be thankful for a little. It is a
great bleſſing <pb n="87" facs="tcp:151842:52"/>to have the Scriptures, and any degree
of the Spirit of God to open them to us, in ſhewing to us the Wonders of God
in the Creatures; particularly in the gathering together of the Waters, and
ſetting bounds to their proud Waves, ſaying, <hi>Hither to and no
further;</hi> in cauſing the dry Land to appear, and at the Command of God to
appear with an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Verdure, a beautiful Cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which was the end of
the Third Day's Work: <hi>And the Evening and the Morning were the Third
Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Philoſopher's Third Day's Work is a Separation of the
Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that his Dry Ground ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears with a Vegetative Life in it, which, if
he pleaſes, will ſpring up in his Glaſs: There is in his Ground Beautiful
Colours, Pleaſant Scents, and his Earth <pb n="88" facs="tcp:151842:53"/>while in this
ſtate may not be Unprofitable or Unfruitful, but may be made to bring forth
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in not Unprofitable Fruits, nor is his Verdure unpleaſant to
behold. This is a ſhort Account of the Philoſopher's Third Day's Work. A
better Hand may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the ſhortneſs and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of it.</p>
            <p>The Third Day's Work, as it is wrought Internally, in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
forth the Fruits of the Spirit, is excellently deſcribed in the Scripture:
There is the good Ground ſpoken of, that brings forth Fruit abundantly,
<hi>ſome fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſome ſixty, and ſome an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold:</hi> It is a
bleſſed thing to have the good Ground in us, the Ground that ſtands out
of Dying, out of Repentance, tho' it was once covered with the <hi>Waters,</hi>
it is not now laying again <pb n="89" facs="tcp:151842:53"/>this Foundation of Repentance,
but they go on to bring forth other good Fruits, that they may be rooted and
grounded in Love; <hi>that they may take Root downwards, and bring forth Fruit
upwards; Fruits of Righteouſneſs, Fruits of Renown; that they may be as
Trees planted by the Rivers of Waters, bringing forth Fruit in due
ſeaſon.</hi> How ſhort are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtians of this Work? How then
ſhall we attain to the Seventh Day, the Sabbath of Reſt? However, the Work
of this Day is very good: <hi>And the Evening and the Morning is the Third
Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Fourth Day's Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Brightneſs appears before me
with ſuch Splendor, as is ready to dazle my weak ſight: wonderful
Brightneſs hinders our <pb n="90" facs="tcp:151842:54"/>ſight as much almoſt as
Darkneſs. O glorious Sun of Righteouſneſs, ariſe in my Soul! Enlighten
my Darkneſs: Let the Shadows flee away: <hi>In thy Light let me ſee
Light:</hi> Strengthen my Optick Faculty, that I may look within the Vail, and
behold Thee, Thou Sun of Suns; the Brightneſs of the Fathers Glory: I can
ſee but little of Thee; I can know but little of Thee; I cannot Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend
Thee; do thou Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend me, Surround me with thy Brightneſs, Gather me up
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Self, that Inferiour Lights may be under my feet, that I may no
longer be governed by their Influences, but may be under the immediate Conduct
of thy Light World, where they need not the Light of the Sun, for thy Self is
the Light thereof: When ſhall it be ſaid to thy <pb n="91" facs="tcp:151842:54"/>Church,
<hi>Ariſe and ſhine, for thy Light is come?</hi> Even ſo, come Lord
JESUS, come quickly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And God ſaid, Let there be Lights in the Firmament of the
Heaven to ſeparate the Day from the Night; and let them be for Signs and for
Seaſons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and let them give Light on the Earth. And God made
two great Lights, the greater Light to rule the Day, the leſſer Light to
rule the Night; He made alſo the Stars; and God ſet them in the Firmament
to ſhine upon the Earth, and to rule the Night and the Day, and ſeparate
the Light from the Darkneſs: And God ſaw that it was good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God by his Spirit made the Heavens, and by his Spirit he
garniſhed and embelliſhed the Heavens: The Firmament was before a beautiful
Looking-Glaſs, it was an admirable one indeed, <pb n="92" facs="tcp:151842:55"/>when the
lovely Forms of Bodies of Light were to be ſeen in it. <hi>God ſaid, Let
there be Lights in the Firmament:</hi> This was not only to Adorn, but for many
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Uſes, for Signs and for Seaſons; They ſign and ſignify out
much to the Inhabitants of this lower World; they have a Voice to us, if we
could under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it; there is no Tongue nor Language where their Voice is
not heard, but how few under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Language? They were to give Light on
the Earth, Light is one of the moſt comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Bleſſings we have; it is
one of the good Gifts that comes from the Father of Lights. If it were ask'd,
Hath the Light a Father? As <hi>Job</hi> was ask'd concerning the Rain: We
might anſwer, It hath a Divine Original: For the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament is a Mirror, as
it ſhews <pb n="93" facs="tcp:151842:55"/>to us the Births and Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the
upper Light World, the Superceleſtial Sun and Moon, and Stars, the ſeven
Spirits of God, the ſeven Golden Lamps ſhew themſelves in their various
Lights, and put forth their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences in the viſible Heavens, from thence
they are conveyed down to our lower World, and we have our Sun, and Moon, and
Stars in the Earth, we have our Sun <hi>Centralis,</hi> as ſome
Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher calls it, I think <hi>Sandivogius:</hi> Some other Enlightned
Perſon ſaith, <hi>There is Heaven above, and Heaven beneath; know this, and
be happy.</hi> I mention this in this place, becauſe the Mineral Kingdom hath
ſome ſhare in this Fourth Days Work; for when the Lights of the Firmament
were made to ſhine forth, being a Reflection from the moſt glorious Upper 
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:151842:56"/>Light World, they did not reſt there ſo, but that they
put forth Themſelves into a Birth, into a Reflection or Mirror in this Lower
World; but here the Chriſtal is ſo thick, it is hard ſeeing through it,
the Fall hath ſo much mudded this Principle, this Lower Earth: Beſides, our
Sun and Moon are but the Refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of a Reflection, the Shadow of a Shadow:
Therefore we muſt dig deep for this Wiſdom as for hid Treaſures, and we
ſhall ſee Wiſdom hath builded her Houſe, ſo as to lay her ſeven
Pillars deep in the very Foundation, in the very Center of all things. I was
ready to wonder that the Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Kingdom was not deſcribed, as well as the
Creation of the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getable and Animal, in this firſt Chapter of
<hi>Geneſis,</hi> till my Eyes were opened, to ſee it did belong 
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151842:56"/>to this Fourth Day's Work. And now I ſee more clearly the
deep Significancy of <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Bleſſing, which hath contained in
it the Sweetneſs of Heaven above, and the Deep lying beneath, the ſweet
Increaſe of the Sun and of the Moon. Lord, after this ſight, let me no more
think any of thy Creatures mean or little; let me be always thankful for the
leaſt of thy Favours: Nothing can be little that comes from Thee, thou Being
of all Beings: Thou haſt nothing little to give: All thy Works are wonderful,
in Wiſdom haſt thou made them all: Thy Footſteps are glorious, thy
Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtool is richly adorned: All thy Ways are Pleaſantneſs, all thy
Paths are Peace. I deſire to be in Subjection to Thee, thou Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of my
Spirit, that I may live, that I may live to praiſe, <pb n="96" facs="tcp:151842:57"/>live
to love, and to adore thee for ever. The lower Sun, Moon and Stars, that
inhabit our Earth, are for the uſe of Man; eſpecially a wiſe Man, who
knows their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Nature and Uſe, and when he intends to improve them for
the health of his Body, or benefit of his Eſtate, he makes them to ſhine in
his Firmament; and they are to him for Signs and Seaſons, by which to govern
his Work; they are to enlighten his Earth, to make it fruitful, to bring forth
their own bright Forms, till his véry Earth is throughout enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
and comes to be it ſelf a bright ſhining Sun. This Fourth Day's Work is
figured out in Man, who is the Little World in the Frame of his outward Body,
as is ſaid in the 12th of the <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes, Whilſt the Sun is not
dark, nor the Light, nor the Moon, nor the <pb n="97" facs="tcp:151842:57"/>Stars:</hi> The
Fall of Man Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lights, and laid them liable to Darkneſs: It
entied in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the very Soul and Spirit, and darkned the Light there. But when
the Spirit of the Lord comes to work the New Birth, the New Creation, this
Fourth Day's Work comes to be known in the Soul, O who can expreſs the
glorious Splendor if it! When the Lord himſelf comes to be a Sun and a
Shield! When the Sun of Righteouſneſs doth ariſe with Healing in his
Wings! The Dawning of this Day, the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Redneſs, the Sun Riſing: Who
can expreſs the unutterable Sweetneſs and Strength that is felt in the
happy Soul that is thus ſhined upon! But to have this Sun ſhine brighter
and brighter, to the perfect Day, to increaſe into the Light of ſeven Days!
O <pb n="98" facs="tcp:151842:58"/>may a poor low humble Soul that feels a little
Refreſhment from the Beams of this Sun, lie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate till it feels that
it is throughout penetrated and filled, till it is cloathed with the Sun, and
hath the Moon under its Feet, that it may go forth in the power of this Sun as
a Giant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed with Wine, and as a ſtrong Man to run a Race. O my Soul,
lie low; proſtrate thy ſelf at the Feet of thy <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S;</hi> in
ſilence wait his pleaſure; ſtir not up thy Beloved till he pleaſe. He
hath ſometimes viſited a Soul with ſuch Favours as hath made it
ſing.</p>
            <lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>ſilent Waiting I do find</l>
                  <l>A Treaſure opens in my Mind:</l>
                  <l>Turn in, my Soul, turn in and ſee</l>
                  <l>The fulneſs of this Treaſury.</l>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:151842:58"/>
                  <l>'Twas placed here by thee, O Lord,</l>
                  <l>'Tis opened by thy Living Word?</l>
                  <l>'Tis he himſelf doth keep the Key</l>
                  <l>Of all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hidden
Myſtery.</l>
                  <l>He is my Sun of Righteouſneſs,</l>
                  <l>Who my whole Perſon doth poſſeſs:</l>
                  <l>He is my Gold tried in the Fire,</l>
                  <l>He is my Cloathing, my Attire:</l>
                  <l>He is my Food, on him I feed,</l>
                  <l>And find him to be Meat indeed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now proſtrate Soul, do thou ariſe,</l>
                  <l>For thou haſt won the glorious Prize:</l>
                  <l>Do not ſit ſighing here alone,</l>
                  <l>Since thou this happy Day haſt known.</l>
                  <l>The Lovely Garland thou haſt won,</l>
                  <l>Thy Head is wreathed with the Sun.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <p>The Fifth Day's Work of Creation was, The Lord's call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth
the Prolifick Virtue of the Water and Air, which was <pb n="100" facs="tcp:151842:59"/>immediately obeyed, and they brought forth abundantly. <hi>And God
ſaid, Let the Waters bring forth abundantly the moving Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that hath
life, and Fowl that may fly above the Earth, in the open Firmament of Heaven.
And God created great Whales,</hi> &amp;c. This word <hi>abundantly</hi> is
twice uſed in the account of the Fifth Day's Work; this ſhews the abundant
quantity of Water that there was to bring forth, and the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of
Creatures that were brought forth of Fiſh and Fowl, which are innumerable,
and wonderfully various in their ſize, ſhape, and other qualities; their
Number being ſo wonderful, and beyond comprehenſion, their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion
of ſize was wiſely made the moſt vaſtly diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate of any of
the other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; the Whale being of the <pb n="101" facs="tcp:151842:59"/>largeſt
Bulk of all living Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and therefore may be called the Chief of all the
ways and works of God; and as Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> obſerves, in his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
Book of Natural Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, There is bred in a liquid ſubſtance, in
Vinegar, the ſmall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Creature; ſo that there is room left for wonderful
Variety to come between, which is admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably filled up with great Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety. O
bleſſed Eternity! that will give Time and Capacity to ſee the Wonders of
the Ways and Works of God! To ſee them in their Original, not only in a
Glaſs, in ſhadowy Repreſentations; the great quantity and prolifick
Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Waters, is ſeen in their wonderful Encreaſe, which is ſeen
now in their Spawning and bringing forth Multitudes at once; one Fiſh
bringing forth a <pb n="102" facs="tcp:151842:60"/>greater Number at one time, than any
other Creature doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce in many years. The Fowls, thoſe curious Aerial
Inhabitants, are very admirable; they alſo were the Fifth Day's Work, and
tho' they inhabit the Air, the Water is only mentioned as the cauſe of their
Production, by the power of God; which proves what I have before ſaid of the
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finity between the Water and Air; and there were ſome of theſe Creatures
made, as it were, of a Middle Nature, as Fiſh that fly, and Fowl that ſwim.
Theſe Inhabitants of the Aerial Region are very worthy Contemplation, their
excellent Situation, curious Make, variety of Colour, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Employment,
admirable Oeconomy or Government, are all cauſe of much Wonder. There is no
ſort of ſublunary Creatures <pb n="103" facs="tcp:151842:60"/>I would ſo ſoon change
my Make with, as theſe: Their Aerial Bodies are ſo light, their motion is
ſwift. <hi>David</hi> was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to envy their getting ſo near the Altars,
he deſired the Wings of a Dove, to fly away, and be at reſt: Their
Employment is pleaſant, chearfully ſinging their Creators praiſe: They
are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately under their Creator's bountiful Care and Proviſion; they
ſow not, nor reap, yet are taken care of, and have their Meat in due
ſeaſon: I cannot but particularly admire the Bee, that pretty little
Chymiſt, that knows how to ſeparate the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: We may learn Natural
and Moral Philoſophy from this little Inſect: It induſtriouſly works,
and wiſely improves the matter that it works upon, by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating the
Precious from the <pb n="104" facs="tcp:151842:61"/>Vile: Their Government is Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent;
there is Superiority for Orders ſake, and yet love makes an Equality; they
dwell in their little Houſes one by another without encroaching, and yet
communicating; tho' there is ſomething of particularity, it hath one
Foundation, and is cloſely joyned, ſo that it encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes into a common
ſtock. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but much admire this Order of Beings, the winged
Choriſters. If I could underſtand the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of Nature, they would all
teach me much to know the God of Nature, who hath made them, and taught them,
and takes care of them continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally.</p>
            <p>In the Philoſophers Fifth Day's Work, there is the Exaltation of
Eagles, the Doves of <hi>Diana,</hi> whoſe meek Natures might teach their 
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:151842:61"/>Maſters Patience; their <hi>Phaenix</hi> is their moſt
Noble Bird, for out of its Aſhes is produced and doth ariſe a young One
more Noble.</p>
            <p>In the Inword Work upon the Minds of Men, there is a great Advance
of the Work, towards a finiſhing the New Creation, the New Birth, and may be
call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Fifth Day's Work, when we are made to mount up with Wings as
Eagles. It is a bleſſed thing to know this Fifth Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to be
accompliſhed in us, when we come to be above the perturbation of the
Elements, when we dwell in the Upper Region, in Serenity and Stillneſs, in
the One pure Element. If we have Faith as a grain of Muſtard-ſeed, it will
grow up till at laſt it will become a great Tree, that the Fowls of the Air
ſhall lodge in the Branches, our own Spirits <pb n="106" facs="tcp:151842:62"/>will come
to dwell in this beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Tree of Faith, which is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Life than we knew
before; and other good Spirits will inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit with us, that we ſhall ſay
with the Spouſe, <hi>The time of the ſinging of Birds is come, and the
Voice of the Turtle is heard in our Land:</hi> We ſhall joyn with Quires of
Angels, to ſing Hymns of Praiſe to our God and King; Hallelujah,
Hallelujah. Some Souls are redeemed, and brought to this ſtate; but O when
ſhall the Church be brought from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Pots, from amongſt the
ſoil and impurity that cleaves to them? When ſhall ſhe ariſe like a
Bird of Paradiſe, with her Wings of yellow Gold? O my Soul, wreſtle in
ſecret with thy God, that this may be accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that there may be a
going on to the Sixth Day's Work.</p>
            <pb n="107" facs="tcp:151842:62"/>
            <p>Moreover the Lord ſaid, <hi>Let the Earth bring forth the living
thing after its kind, Cattel and every creeping thing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And it
was ſo.</hi> Furthermore, <hi>God ſaid, Let us make Man in our Image,</hi>
&amp;c. Read to the end of the Chapter. The Lord may open more to thee (whoever
thou art) than to me, who know nothing, but am a little Child; I am become a
Fool, that I may be made Wiſe: I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that my bleſſed Jeſus may be
made of God to me Wiſdom. 'Tis the Fools and ſimple Ones to whom Wiſdom
cries: She lifts up her Voice, and ſaith, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo is ſimple, turn in
hither:</hi> And to a poor ſimple One, as I am, ſhe may ſhew the
Excellency of the Six Day's Work of Creation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Lord ſaid, Let the Earth bring forth:</hi> This was
a pure Earth, as it came forth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately <pb n="108" facs="tcp:151842:63"/>from the Lord,
as it was the immediate Product or Birth of his Spirit: And when the dry Land
did appear at the Command of God, the Lord ſaw that it was good: And tho' at
the firſt appearance the dry Earth had not ſo great a Luſtre as
after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when it was beautified and adorned, but was partly like a calcined
Earth; the Fire, and Water, and Air, being in a great degree ſeparated from
it; yet when the Lord by his powerful Word call'd forth its Virtue, it ſhew'd
it ſelf to have an admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Life in it: And indeed the Earth it ſelf was
exceedingly more pure, beautiful, lovely, than ſince the Curſe: It did far
excel in Colour, Virtue, Clarity and Brightneſs; that all the Creatures that
were then the immediate product of this Earth, were like <pb n="109" facs="tcp:151842:63"/>it ſelf, very good, very lovely, and tranſparent; ſuch were then
the Plants, the Beaſts, and the Man, whoſe Name ſignifies the Red Earth
of which he was made. Whoſoever hath his Eyes opened by the Lord to ſee the
Paradiſical State of things, they will ſee the Plants to appear
Chriſtaline, like precious Stones, and all other things proportionably
advanced to a moſt Noble Excellent ſtate; which I doubt not ſome
Perſons have ſeen while in the Body, more clearly than my ſelf. Could we
ſee, or elſe believe, that the Beaſts were ever ſuch Excellent
Creatures, and capable of being made ſo again, there would not be ſuch
cruelty uſed towards our fellow-Creatures as there is, when we ſee they are
part of the ſame Day's Work with our ſelves, of the Sixth Day's Work; and
that <pb n="110" facs="tcp:151842:64"/>they were very Excellent in their Make; and that by
the Fall of Mankind, who was made the Lord of them, the poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures came to
ſink with him into a low deplorable ſtate of Miſery: ſure we ſhall
commiſerate them, we ſhall gain the true Empire over them by behaving our
ſelves towards them with much love, and ſome reſpect, tho' as to
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Creatures; yet this love will gain our true Empire over the
Creatures. When this Spirit of Love goes forth, that Promiſe ſhall be made
good, <hi>That the Lion ſhall lie down with the Lamb, and a little Child
ſhall lead them:</hi> While we are wrathful toward the Creatures, it ſtirs
up wrath and enmity in them; but when we rule them in love, with wiſdom, they
eaſily ſubject themſelves to us; when we rule more from a 
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151842:64"/>Spirit given us of God to govern, than from a deſire in
us, or a will to have Superiority over our fellow-Creatures.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord, Let not my Sins, my Struggle with thy Will, any longer
hinder thy great Bleſſings from go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth in the Earth, to the
Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe of the poor groaning Creatures, Man and Beaſt; but help me to
groan with them, for the glorious Liberty of the Sons of God. And if an evening
muſt go before this morning, help me to ſubmit to it, and help all thy
People to ſubmit in holy Reſignation to thy Divine Will, thou Soveraign
Lord of Lords, and King of Kings; to whom be aſcribed all Power, Might, and
Dominion for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus have I been enabled to ſay ſomething of the firſt part
of the Sixth Day's Work. Now the Lord help me to know my ſelf; 
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151842:65"/>ſuch Knowledge it too wonderful for me.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So God created Man in his own Image:</hi> O that the Vail
might be more perfectly drawn away, that clouds this Image in me, that I may
ſee its brightneſs ſo clearly ſhine forth in me, that what I ſee and
feel I may declare. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Image doth conſiſt in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitude and
Order, in the Union of Truth, Being, and Goodneſs; God made Man upright, he
was made ſincere, in ſimplicity and integrity: the uprightneſs of Man is
the Image of God, as he is a pure Unity, the One from whom all Variety flows;
and this Image of God is moſt admirable, moſt lovely; thus God himſelf
chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cterizeth <hi>Job, Haſt thou conſidered my Servant Job, a Perfect
Man, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright?</hi> When the Lord had thus deſcribed <hi>Job,</hi>
preſently he <pb n="113" facs="tcp:151842:65"/>was ſet up as a Mark for the Enemy of
Mankind to ſhoot at: Alſo <hi>Job</hi>'s Friends and others try their Skill
upon the good Man, being ſtirred up by the Evil One. There is nothing ſo
much hated by the Evil One, nor wicked Men; as Integrity and Uprightneſs:
There is nothing to which they are ſo much contrary, becauſe all ſin is a
breach of the Unity: It dwells in Contrariety, Diſorder, Confuſion; but
when we once gain the bleſſed Image again of Uprightneſs, there is
nothing ſo ſecures a Soul from evil Spirits, and Men, and from the ſtrife
of Tongues, as this. There is a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in the Scriptures, <hi>Integrity
and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs ſhall preſerve me:</hi> or to that purpoſe. <hi>Mark
the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man, and behold the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright, for the end of that man is
Peace:</hi> from this Root an Admirable <pb n="114" facs="tcp:151842:66"/>Variety doth flow:
God made Man Upright; upon this Tree in the midſt of the Garden did grow
Twelve manner of Fruits; Righteouſneſs, Holineſs, Love, Peace, Joy,
Humility, Patience, and other excellent Fruits: here grows forth a numerous
variety; but all in a Beautiful Order and Harmony; in the Tree of Mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of
Good and Evil, there is Contrariety and Diſorder, there is Breaking in pieces
and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; but where there is Integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we ſhall be as Mount-Sion
that cannot be moved: Man was made in this bleſſed ſtate of Recti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude
and and Order, Uprightneſs and Integrity of Spirit and Soul; and alſo his
very Body was of an Excellent Proportion, Tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Brightneſs,
Admirable Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, to ſet out this Curious Structure; we ſhall know more 
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151842:66"/>of this, when we ſhall be made to return into the
Paradiſical State more fully; that the very Body may partake of it, and the
Youth be Renewed like the Eagles: it is but few yet know any thing of this;
ſome there are, though I am but waiting for the Redemption of the Body.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Image of God Created he him, Male and Female Created he
them:</hi> Man was in every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect made after the Image of God, the Female
as well as the Male.</p>
            <p>I do not ſee that <hi>Adam</hi> ſinned in deſiring to bring
forth his Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Self: It was before the Fall, and was no part of the Fall; it
was a Variety, but not Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety; it was a Pattern of things in the
Heavenly; Diſtinction is conſiſtent with Unity: <hi>Marriage is
Honourable, and the Bed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led:</hi> 
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:151842:67"/>True Marriage
is very Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable. The Apoſtle ſaith it repreſents Chriſt and the
Church, who when the Spirit of God hath made ready, ſhe will be the Bride,
the Lambs Wife. After theſe Conſiderations, methinks none ſhould dare to
profane that State.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Lord bleſſed them, and ſaid, Be fruitful and
multiply, and repleniſh the Earth, and ſubdue it, and have Dominion,</hi>
&amp;c. This Authority was given to the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male as well as to the Male;
therefore it is unjuſt in any to ſay they are not capable to Rule; they are
in moſt caſes certainly to give Man the Superiority; yet the Woman is
capable to receive a Spirit of Government when the Lord pleaſes to give it:
But it is certainly more happy to be Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned, than to Govern, unleſs 
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151842:67"/>God calls for ſuch a Service. The ſubordinate Station
of a Woman in Governing a Family, which is uſually allowed them, is
Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Comfortable, if it is faithfully and prudently mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged. But
Women are capable of other Employments than theſe: Their Mother Wiſdom who
hath builded her Houſe, and hewn out her ſeven Pillars; hath called
ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ones to come in hither; and ſhe doth not exclude Females, but they
may receive the Law from her Mouth; ſhe will open her hid Treaſures to
them, and ſhew them that Wiſdom is better than Gold, yea, than much fine
Gold, better than Rubies; that the Merchandiſe is better than Silver, and the
gain thereof than much fine Gold: If Man did but know himſelf, he would
ſoon find Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom's Golden Mine: If Man did <pb n="118" facs="tcp:151842:68"/>but know
and would conſider his Divine Original, his admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Make in his
Paradiſical ſtate, that his outward Form: was ſo lovely, his Noble Soul
was eaſily ſeen through it, ſurely he would not behave himſelf
unſeemly to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his own Body, which is a Temple for the holy Ghoſt to
dwell in, as the bleſſed Apoſtle tells us. And did Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
conſider, though now they are in a diſtinct Exiſtence, they were once
One, and when they are United in Marriage come to be ſo again; ſurely they
would behave themſelves well in that Relation, each in love and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
eſteeming the other; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially let the Woman be careful to perform her
Duty, for ſhe was firſt in the Tranſgreſſion, ſhe hath the more
need to watch and pray, that ſhe enter not into <pb n="119" facs="tcp:151842:68"/>Temptation. When this Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is thus lived in, with this regard to
themſelves, and one towards another, it is a holy hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſtate; and <hi>if
ye be holy,</hi> the Apoſtle tells us, <hi>then are your Children alſo holy
Jacob Behm,</hi> that enlightened man, ſaith, <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to get your
Children good Souls.</hi> This ſtate ſo lived in, is not unbecoming a
Paradiſical ſtate, and certainly entails a great Bleſſing upon
Poſterity. But notwithſtanding there is an Excellency in the Paradiſical
ſtate, yet the Heavenly is moſt Excellent, wherein there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Male
nor Female, Bond nor Free, but we are all one in Chriſt Jeſus. Our
bleſſed Saviour tells us, <hi>In Heaven there is neither Marrying, nor
giving in Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, but we ſhall be like the Angels in Heaven.</hi> And as
all Variety <pb n="120" facs="tcp:151842:69"/>proceeds from Unity, ſo they muſt return
to Unity again. Chriſt himſelf ſhall deliver up the Kingdom to the
Father, and God ſhall be all in all. Unity is the Beginning and End of all
things, and Reſt is the Beginning and End of all things; which leads me to
the Seventh Day's Reſt: <hi>The Evening and the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was the Sixth
Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let all Creatures praiſe the Lord, my Soul ſhall bleſs
him while I have a being. Glory to him that ſits upon the Throne for ever and
ever, Amen, Halle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah. <hi>The Lord Omnipotent reigns: Let the Earth rejoyce,
and the multitude of Iſles be glad. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, O my Soul; Rejoyce in the Lord
evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Wiſe Mans Sixth Day, is, When his Work comes to, Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality,
ſhall I ſay? It hath then <pb n="121" facs="tcp:151842:69"/>a Paradiſical Body, and
rather more then ſo, for it can penetrate Bodies; and it is not the Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
of Bodies to have Penetration of Dimenſions. But draw a Vail here, leſt
Unhallowed Hands Touch, or their Eyes See: <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is a thirſt, let him
come:</hi> If he is not athirſt for Gold, but for Wiſdom, he will find
Wiſdom's Houſe Open to Receive the Hungry and Thirſty; And for ſuch
ſhe hath prepared a Feaſt, ſhe hath mingled her Wine, and made ready her
De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licacies.</p>
            <p>The Internal Sixth Day's Work is, When we come to the ſtate of
Manhood: To be a Man in Chriſt Jeſus, is a bleſſed happy ſtate; nay,
to be a Babe in Chriſt is ſo, but much more to be a ſtrong Man: There is
Food prepared for all theſe ſtates, <pb n="122" facs="tcp:151842:70"/>Milk for Babes,
Meat for Men, ſtrong Meat for ſtrong Men, when we grow up to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
of the ſtature appointed to us in Chriſt Jeſus. All true Life and growth
is from our being united to Jeſus Chriſt our Head, who will perfect and
compleat his Body.</p>
            <p>Now to our bleſſed and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious JESUS, who is able to
per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect what concerns us, and to ſanctifie us wholly in Soul, Body and
Spirit: To Him be Glory, Honour and Praiſe for ever. He will in his own time
bring us to the Day of Reſt, the perfect Number Seven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And God Reſted the Seventh Day: So God bleſſed the
Seventh Day, and hallowed it.</hi> This Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Day was a Day without Clouds;
It is not ſaid of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Day, <hi>The Evening and the 
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151842:70"/>Morning were</hi> that <hi>Day,</hi> as it was ſaid of
the Firſt, and ſo on to the Sixth: Indeed the Natural Day that appears to
this lower World, is as other Days; and to thoſe who dwell in the mixtures of
Light and Darkneſs, Good and Evil; nay, they love Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs rather than
Light; to them this Day hath not much more in it than other Days. But the
All-glorious God, tho' he condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to work and operate in this
Principle, wherein is ſome mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Darkneſs, and we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſay
God was in the Darkneſs; yet he dwells not in the Darkneſs, he dwells in
the Light, he Reſts there; he entred into his own Light Principle, and
Reſts there: <hi>God is Light, and in him is no Darkneſs at all:</hi> He is
Love, Anger is his ſtrange Work; ſo it ſhould be with his 
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151842:71"/>Children: <hi>Anger reſts in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of Fools.</hi>
If a Prophet or Propheteſs have a Command from God to go forth with a
Meſſage of Wrath, a Denuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Threatning, they muſt be obedient;
but they muſt not reſt in it, they muſt not ſtir up the Wrath, they
muſt rather qualifie it with the Meek Love of JESUS; there they may Reſt,
in him they find Reſt to their Souls.</p>
            <p>I did in the beginning of my Writings ſay ſomething, as I was
enabled, of the Reſt and Repoſe of the glorious Deity, before his going
forth into Manifeſtation or Operation: It was then, and is now an harmonious
Stillneſs, a ſweet Repoſe; only now there is an Additional Joy, <hi>The
Lord ſaw his Works, and they were all very good:</hi> He was pleaſed to
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <pb n="125" facs="tcp:151842:71"/>his Works, having ſo much of his own Image of
Goodneſs in them; this cauſeth Joy in God himſelf: And tho' Sin did Cloud
and Vail this Image, yet the Lord, in infinite Mercy and Wiſdom, did by
Jeſus Chriſt, reſtore the faln Creation of Man, break down the middle
Wall of Partition, not only between Jew and Gentile, but between God and Man:
And our bleſſed Lord Jeſus himſelf is the New and Living Way, by which
we enter in within the Vail now. When one Sinner returns, there is Joy in
Heaven over one Sinner that repents, and the Father receives the Prodigal with
Joy, till at laſt the whole Work ſhall be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed, and every
Creature, of things in Heaven, things on Earth, and under the Earth, ſhall
bleſs and praiſe the Lord for <pb n="126" facs="tcp:151842:72"/>ever. O what a
bleſſed Sabbath will that be! But who can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs any thing of it? Only
the Lord makes a poor weary heavy laden Soul to feel ſomething of it in
himſelf, when we die in the Lord, and reſt from our Labours: When we die
into the Lord, out of all things beſides, we ſhall know what it is to
Reſt, and to rejoyce with Joy unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and glorious. To reſt from our
Labours, and to have our Works follow us, this is not a working for Life by
Legal Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances; it is rather a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a Principle of Life, where
the Works follow, and go not before the Life. But there is ſomething more
than this, there is a State of Reſt and Joy, wherein the Works of the Spirit
that are wrought in us, when the Lord works in us to Will and to 
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151842:72"/>Do, follow us, and are ſet before us, to cauſe in us
Joy and Rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing. To look back upon our own Works, which are perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med from
a Legal Selfiſh Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, cauſeth no true Joy nor Reſt, but rather
lifting up in Pride and Self-will: But in the true Work of the Spirit, tho' we
may <hi>go forth weeping, bearing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſeed, we ſhall return
rejoycing, bringing our Sheaves with us.</hi> Theſe Fruits of the Spirit,
Love, Joy, Peace, follow ſuch a Soul into the Reſt and ſweet Repoſe it
attains here, and alſo into the Reſt which remains for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of
God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lord, Let me know ſuch a laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, permanent, ſixt
Reſt, as may not have Evening nor Morning, but may be a Day without a Cloud,
that I may have thy Light ſhining in me brighter and brighter, to the 
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151842:73"/>perfect Day, when thou wilt be my Light for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Wiſe Men, whom God himſelf hath Enlightned, are the only
Wiſe Men, and the moſt Happy; having the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Repoſe which the World
cannot give, nor take away: Wiſdom enables them to work, and when their Work
is come to the Seventh Day of Perfection, they reſt from their Labours; their
Work which was bulky and laborious, comes to be eaſily portable pleaſant
Employment, which they account rather Reſt than Labour; and the effects of
their Works, and the Work it ſelf, follows them where-ever they go; and ſo
mighty Works ſhew forth themſelves in them, as in their glorious Lord and
Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, who promiſed that <hi>the Works that he did, they ſhould do 
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151842:73"/>alſo:</hi> Now theſe Works ſhew forth themſelves
in them, more in their Patience, Stillneſs and Reſt, than in all their
buſie Working. 'Tis but little Man hath to do in inward or outward Working,
when he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted himſelf and all his ways to the Lord. Now it is a
bleſſed thing to feel any beginnings of this ſweet Day, this holy happy
ſtate of Reſt, within; tho' it may not be brought forth thro' the whole
Perſon: But the Lord is the Rock, and his Work is perfect; He will perfect
what concerns thoſe that truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wait patiently on the Lord, O my Soul, for he will give thee
Reſt for the Days wherein he hath affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted thee: O that the Peace of God,
that paſſeth all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, may guard my Heart and Mind, that no 
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151842:74"/>Storm nor Tempeſt may break in; that I could retire into
my ſtrong Hold, as a Priſoner of Hope, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the Redemption of my
Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and not mine only, but of the whole groaning Creation, that the Year of
Jubilee may be known to them, when there ſhall be proclaimed Liberty for the
Captives, that the Creation may be brought forth into the glorious Liberty of
the Sons of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O happy time, when <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall become the
Praiſe of the whole Earth; when the Lord ſhall ſet his King upon the holy
Hill of <hi>Sion;</hi> when our King ſhall be exalted by and upon a People
who are as a barren Mountain, nothing in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; that ſo our King and
our God, the bleſſed JESUS, may Reign, to whom all Power in Heaven and
Earth is given, and <pb n="131" facs="tcp:151842:74"/>of whoſe Dominion there is no End:
To whom be Glory, and Honour, and Bleſſing, and Praiſe, for ever, and for
ever, Amen, Hallelujah.</p>
            <lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Great Lord of Lords, and King of Kings,</l>
                  <l>Thou mak'ſt my dry and thirſty Earth to ſing,</l>
                  <l>And in the Deſart cauſeth a New Spring.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Awake, my Soul, and ſing <hi>Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah's</hi> Praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Who giveth Life, and from the Dead doth raiſe:</l>
                  <l>Mercy and Goodneſs are in all his Ways.</l>
               </lg>
            </lg>
            <div type="hymns">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:151842:75"/>
               <head>Hymns.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>IN lowly Meekneſs I will dwell,</l>
                  <l>The Lilly of the Vale is ſweet;</l>
                  <l>Ofttimes the loftieſt Cedars fall,</l>
                  <l>And then alas their fall is great.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Sp'rit that in the Myrtles moved,</l>
                  <l>Is a pure breath of holy Air;</l>
                  <l>Sometimes theſe Shrubs are viſited</l>
                  <l>Whilſt higher Trees neglected are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come my Beloved o're Mountain top,</l>
                  <l>Come skipping o're the higheſt Hill;</l>
                  <l>Let thy Winds on my Garden blow,</l>
                  <l>Do thou with ſweets my Spices fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:151842:75"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>When thou bright Sun vouchſaf'ſt to ſhine</l>
                  <l>On my Beloved <hi>Sharon</hi> Roſe,</l>
                  <l>It hath its ſweetneſs all from thee,</l>
                  <l>And with thee takes a ſweet Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>It opens as the Morning fair,</l>
                  <l>When thou bright Sun art pleas'd to appear,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhuts up all its hidden ſtore,</l>
                  <l>Till thy Sight does again draw near.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus I'm a Garden clos'd to all,</l>
                  <l>A Fountain ſeal'd to all but thee,</l>
                  <l>Leſt little Foxes ſhould ſpoil my Vine,</l>
                  <l>The tender Grape planted by thee.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:151842:76"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And leſt the Silver-running Stream,</l>
                  <l>That is pure as it comes from thee,</l>
                  <l>Should mingle, with the muddy Earth</l>
                  <l>Partake of its impurity.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="hymns">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:151842:76"/>
               <head>Hymns.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>OH how ſhall I the praiſes ſing</l>
                  <l>Of our great God and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King,</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſs his Spirit doth indite,</l>
                  <l>What I ſhould ſing, what I ſhould write!</l>
                  <l>His Spirit doth Secrets Reveal,</l>
                  <l>He opens the Myſtick ſeventh Seal,</l>
                  <l>The ſeventh Seal, the ſeventh Thunder</l>
                  <l>Opens in me, a ſacred Wonder.</l>
                  <l>He leads me to the Centre deep,</l>
                  <l>Where Spirits dark their Priſon keep.</l>
                  <l>Yet in this doleful Night does dwell</l>
                  <l>A Light, that Conquers Death and Hell.</l>
                  <l>For from the dark and hidden Ground,</l>
                  <l>The Light ariſing may be found,</l>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:151842:77"/>
                  <l>I have ſeen a darkſome gloomy ſhade</l>
                  <l>Aweful and Majeſtick made,</l>
                  <l>But at Sun-riſing with his light,</l>
                  <l>Hath been more pleaſing to the ſight,</l>
                  <l>With the ſweet and lovely Green,</l>
                  <l>Guilded with the Sun between.</l>
                  <l>So have I ſeen a Picture fair,</l>
                  <l>Made by Artiſts Hand more rare,</l>
                  <l>When from darkeſt ſhades I ſee,</l>
                  <l>The Light ariſing to a degree,</l>
                  <l>Moſt perfect, pleaſing, and moſt ſweet,</l>
                  <l>Made from Variety ſo great.</l>
                  <l>So have I heard a pleaſing ſound</l>
                  <l>Ariſing from deep Gamuts ground;</l>
                  <l>But Oh my ſpirits, how they fail,</l>
                  <l>When I in this vaſt Ocean ſail.</l>
                  <l>Now I've a deep and hidden ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>From the Centre to the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</l>
                  <l>Moſt holy Spirit keep me ſtill,</l>
                  <l>I may be guided by thy will.</l>
                  <l>Oh how can I deſcribe the fall</l>
                  <l>My ſelf, ſo great a Criminal,</l>
                  <l>Darker than night, darker than ſhade,</l>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:151842:77"/>
                  <l>Or all things elſe that have been made;</l>
                  <l>More ſad than Muſicks deepeſt ground,</l>
                  <l>I muſt my Lamentation ſound.</l>
                  <l>And from this doleful diſmal Cry,</l>
                  <l>I would call all the ſtanders by,</l>
                  <l>To ſee this ſad and tragi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k ſight,</l>
                  <l>Which may the hardeſt Spirits fright.</l>
                  <l>Here you may ſee a Lamb lye ſlain,</l>
                  <l>With the deepeſt, ſharpeſt pain;</l>
                  <l>There you ſee Spirits Captive led,</l>
                  <l>Sure they are free amongſt the dead.</l>
                  <l>Here are Spirits led in Chains,</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder cruel torturing pains;</l>
                  <l>There lye dry and ghaſtly Bones,</l>
                  <l>With hearts more hard than hardeſt ſtones;</l>
                  <l>Here lies ſhrieking, tortur'd Souls</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder ugly Spirits Controuls.</l>
                  <l>Now thoſe that thro' all this can ſee</l>
                  <l>A lovely, beauteous Harmony,</l>
                  <l>Muſt be Baptized of the Spirit,</l>
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:151842:78"/>
                  <l>And his Tincturing Love inherit.</l>
                  <l>The Lamb is made a Sacrifice,</l>
                  <l>But out of Death he does ariſe,</l>
                  <l>And in his riſing gives a Spring</l>
                  <l>Of Light and Life to every thing;</l>
                  <l>The Captiv'd Soul he did ſet free,</l>
                  <l>In Life and Immortality;</l>
                  <l>Such as in darkeſt Chains are led,</l>
                  <l>Are now ariſing from the dead;</l>
                  <l>To dry and ghaſtly Bones does give,</l>
                  <l>Power to Ariſe and Live;</l>
                  <l>The Tortur'd Souls he does unbind,</l>
                  <l>The fouleſt Spirits are calcin'd.</l>
                  <l>But now my Soul fall down and praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Before the Antient of Days;</l>
                  <l>The Praiſes of the Lamb proclaim,</l>
                  <l>Exalt and magnifie his Name.</l>
                  <l>The Holy Spirit do thou adore,</l>
                  <l>Who opens thus his hidden ſtore.</l>
                  <l>The Three in One I'll Celebrate,</l>
                  <l>All things in Love he did Create.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe who are Objects now of woe,</l>
                  <l>They may have Cauſe to think it ſo.</l>
                  <l>All Creatures now bow down and fall,</l>
                  <l>Before the Father of us all,</l>
                  <l>And his high Praiſes with me ſing,</l>
                  <l>Who is our Everlaſting King.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="subpart">
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:151842:78"/>
               <head>A Short Diſcourſe Concerning thoſe Two Great Principles
of Natural Philoſophy, <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Motion.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is the fault of many Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Perſons in their
Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of Natural Things, that they only Speak or Write of them in
their Second Cauſes, and not <hi>ab Origine,</hi> in their firſt Root and
Fountain, the Divine Being, who is the Source of all Being, Bleſſedneſs
and Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and I doubt not this hath been the fault of ſome, who have
had in their Minds a high Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Ever Bleſſed God: Yet this
neglect hath been a great Evil in Three Reſpects.</p>
               <p>Firſt, That they have not as they ought acknowledged God 
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:151842:79"/>in all their Ways, and did not begin with him who is the
Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of all things.</p>
               <p>Secondly, By this they may have miſled ſome of the
Illiterate and Unthinking World, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſome ready to doubt of the
Firſt Cauſe, becauſe theſe Men who they value mention nothing of it,
others think ill of the Men, and the Truths they Diſcourſe of, becauſe
the Ground of all Truth is left out in their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, This kind of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy cannot be ſolid and
ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial, wanting a good Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation. I hope in what I have to ſay
about Matter, and its Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſification, about Motion, and the Origine, Order
and End of it, will be all plainly deduced from <pb n="141" facs="tcp:151842:79"/>the
Almighty Goodneſs, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of them, and return'd to him who is their
Reſt. The Learned Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> tells us, in his Book, called, <hi>The
Origine of Forms and Qualities,</hi> that the World is made of one Univerſal
and Catholick Matter, which is a great Truth, but few or none tells us, what
this Matter is; much leſs, what it was; indeed ſome tells us, it was
Nothing, why then it is ſo ſtill, 'tis not better than in the Paradiſical
State of things; indeed it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, compar'd with its Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; it is
nothing, if it were poſſible to ſeparate it from its Root, but ſince
that cannot be, I will write of it as ſomething, or elſe my Diſcourſe
would ſoon be at an end, for of nothing. It ſhould have but little to
ſay; Matter is a continued Emanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <pb n="142" facs="tcp:151842:80"/>from the Viſible
Heavens, which are a kind of middle Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, between Spirit and Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, they
are Spirit compar'd with Matter, and Matter compared with Spirit: What
Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations are between theſe middle Natures, and the Glorious up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
Light World, I will not now Diſcourſe, but I am ſure they have their
Life, Light, Power, Virtue, all from thence, which if the Viſible Heavens did
not convey to this Lower World, it would be brought al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as near nothing,
as ſome Men imagine it once to have been. The Scriptures teach us the beſt
Natural Philoſophy, when they tell us, the Light is the Life of Man, and
doubtleſs it is ſo of all other Creatures; not by ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning upon them, but
by ſhining in them, being their ſubſtantial <pb n="143" facs="tcp:151842:80"/>Root and
Original; the Sun as a ſecond Cauſe, was not made only to Illuminate the
World to ſhine upon it, but to be the Parent or Father of Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getables, and
other Creatures that do inhabit the Earth; the Sun doth impregnate and ſtir
up the Vegetive Faculty of the Earth, and cauſes it to bring forth firſt
the Root of an Opa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cous Colour like the Earth, in which it is fixt lighter than
that, the Stalk grows up out of the mixture of the Nitrous Azure Air, and the
Sulphureous Yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Earth, which being min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, cauſes the Verdant Stalk and
Leaves, and by a greater Maturation and Ripening of the Subſtances, is
produced the love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Red or Purple, the Glory of the Vegetable Kingdom. How the
Sun, and other Luminous <pb n="144" facs="tcp:151842:81"/>Bodies do produce Minerals, and
and are Conducive to Animal Births, I ſhall not now Diſcourſe, each part
would make a large Tract, that theſe Congregate Bodies of Light are Conducive
to the Production of things, and are the moſt excellent, active Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
Cauſes, is obvious almoſt to our very outward Senſes; but there was a
time when theſe bright Bodies had not a Being, as they now have, and then
they could not produce other Beings, nor give Being to themſelves; the Light
that is the Life of Man, is alſo the Light and Life of theſe Creatures, (of
this bright Sun and Moon) he is a Wiſe and All-powerful Agent who gave them
their ſhining, and when he withdraws his Influences, the Sun ſhall be
turned into Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and the Moon into Blood, <pb n="145" facs="tcp:151842:81"/>
                  <hi>before the great and notable Day of the Lord come,</hi> as the
Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures tell us: And though we have not ſeen this particular change
here mentioned, we know not how ſoon it may be; and however, we have ſeen
enough Alterations upon the whole Face of Viſible Things, to make us know
they are not perfect Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and did not make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but are made and
govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by a Perfect and Intelligent Being</p>
               <p>The Second Principle to be Diſcours'd of about Matter, is,
That the great Bodies of Light, and other Creatures of Bulk, do conſiſt,
and are made up of leſſer Bodies, which we may call A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms, Corpuſcles or
Particles; theſe little parts of Matter have their determinate ſize,
ſhape, <pb n="146" facs="tcp:151842:82"/>ſcituation, colour, in order to conſtitute
ſomething of greater Bulk, Beauty, and Service; the Texture and Joining
together of theſe are contrived by a Wiſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, to conduce to a Noble
End. The motion or moving of theſe little Particles, did at firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce,
as a Second Cauſe, to the making Varieties of Creatures; and it is now highly
conducing to the Changes that paſs upon all material things; which brings me
to the Second Head of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe I principally intended, which is to ſay
ſomething of Motion; Matter had an Occult Principle of Motion hid in its
Nature, not being made of a dull inſenſible nothing, out of I know not what
imaginary, empty ſpace, but was made of an active Subſtance; yet it did not
actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally move in a regular determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <pb n="147" facs="tcp:151842:82"/>Motion, till the
Spirit of the Living God, Moved upon it, and thereby put it into its right
order of moving, and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed the Laws of its Motion, in which courſe
of moving it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to this Day, only to ſhow that he is a Wiſe and Free
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent that moved it at firſt, and continues preſent with it to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect all
its Motions; the uſual Courſe of it hath ſometimes been a little altered,
and new Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip hath been made to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, to ſhow the Soveraignty,
Wiſdom and Power of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and Mover of all things. Some have compared
this World to a Clock-work; that kind of Work, may a little explain to us the
Matter and Motion of this great Machine or Engine, the great World; but in this
they greatly differ, the little Clocks <pb n="148" facs="tcp:151842:83"/>and Watches are
made and put into Motion, but left by the Maker to move a determinate time
without him; or he leaves it to ſome other Agent to carry on the Motions: But
if by Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, or ſome Ignorant Hand, ſomething ſhould come in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
the Wheels, it would wholly ſtop or diſorder the whole Frame; but if the
Wiſe Artiſt brings in any new Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they may be for Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and
Uſe in the Work; this hath been done in the upper Wheels of the great
Clock-work our Viſible Heavens, which proves what I before aſſerted, the
preſence of an Omniſcient Mover: And as the Viſible Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens may be
diſcours'd of, as the upper Wheels of a Clock, for their Circular Motion,
ſo may the Earth, and its Motion, be a <pb n="149" facs="tcp:151842:83"/>little explained,
by comparing it with the Pendulum, that pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates and gravitates the Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of the Earth, being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like this; not as ſome have ſuppoſed,
whirling about its Axis, but moving, as we call it, forward and backward,
Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and Weſtward, which cauſes the Ebbing and Flowing of the Sea;
which whirls not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout like a Whirlpool, but moves conſtantly Eaſt and
Weſt; the cauſe of which I ſhall by and by intimate a little more fully,
that the Viſible Heavens are kept in their Beauty, Order, Motion, by the
Power of Attraction, of Divine Energy, Power, Virtue, from the upper Light
World, I am well aſſured, but how this is performed. I ſhall not more
largely expreſs at preſent, ſuch Knowledge is too wonderful for 
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:151842:84"/>me; yet ſometimes ſuch a little Living Engine as my
ſelf, in its moving up and down this great World, feels ſomething of the
Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Magnetiſm and Attraction in ſuch a manner, as no words can
expreſs fully; yet it is ſuch as gives a little Knowledge of ſuch Powers
and Virtues in their various Degrees and Meaſures through the whole
Univerſe: But to ſpeak of Motion, as it is performed by Second Cauſes, it
is performed in the great World, by the Attraction or Magnetiſm of Light and
Fire; that Fire draws Fiery Subſtances, is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious to common Underſtanding
and Experience. The Lights and Fires of the Viſible Heavens are placed quite
round the Earth, and ſo draw and Attract ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Internal Heat and
Fire contain'd in the Earth; drawing <pb n="151" facs="tcp:151842:84"/>thus every way, as a
Second Cauſe, keeps the Earth and Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter (whereof the whole Globe
conſiſts) in <hi>equalibrio,</hi> but at the Riſing of the Sun, which is
a large Aggregate of Light and Fire, the Earth enclines that way, and at the
Setting, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but that it Conſtantly keeps not this Motion, and no
other, is from the interveening of the Moon, and other Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bodies, which
alſo have the ſtrong Power of Attraction: And there is alſo in the Earth
ſome large Orifices, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which
more ſtrongly may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, and ſo move and encline the Earth; but in what
part of the Globe theſe are placed, I ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther have not read in my little
Knowledge of Geography, or have forgot theſe hints; if wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
conſideration may put ſome <pb n="152" facs="tcp:151842:85"/>more fit Perſon upon the
Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and they may expreſs their Thoughts in a better Method: Some may
ſay theſe indeed are ſome Theoretical Diſcourſes, Particular Opinions
or Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of Things, but of what uſe we know not, either to the
Minds of Men, or their out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Condition: Whether theſe Conſiderations may
be uſeful in the Mechanicks, I know not; to ſuch as have been long Studying
to make ſome Engine with a Perpetual Motion; what they mean
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>petual, I know not; I ſuppoſe
only a long Duration; I am apt to think ſomething of this kind may be made,
that by the Power of Magnetiſm, may continue longer moving than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing
elſe hath been found: But though I ſee ſomething how this may be done,
yet not ſo as to <pb n="153" facs="tcp:151842:85"/>give a perfect Model to any Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; nor
can I at preſent work it with my own Hands, I know not what time may produce
of this kind; I am not yet any good Mathematician.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Theſe two Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Philoſophy,
<hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Motion</hi> ſimply conſidered, may, if made uſe
of, produce things uſeful to the Health of Mankind, and may cauſe ſtrange
Changes in many Subſtances; I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance only in an Experiment, I think
call'd the <hi>Torecellian</hi> Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment, performed in the King of
<hi>Denmark</hi>'s Laboratory, where the Compact Body of Gold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for a
conſiderable time ground in a Gold or Steel Mill, was ſo opened and
changed, as to become a high uſeful Medicine for the Bodies of Mankind; and 
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:151842:86"/>I know not; but in this way it may be made capable of
penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Mineral Subſtances, and thereby become uſeful many ways,
wherein the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of what hath been ſaid, may be uſeful to the
Minds of Men; I ſhall ſay a little, and ſo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this
Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>The Great and Good God did make all things, and put them into
motion for great and wiſe Ends; nothing moves that it may move, but that it
may be of ſome uſe and ſervice while it moves, and in order to
Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Reſt; hardly any Man moves, but he intends Health or
Buſineſs, and in a little time Reſt: The motion of the whole Creation is
in order to Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Reſt, and this is only by terminating in the
Bleſſed Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <pb n="155" facs="tcp:151842:86"/>of Being: Some Creatures do wander,
and ſeem to go out of their way; but he that guides all their motions, knows
how to reduce them to their true end, his Glory, and their Happineſs. There
is a Line in the Heavens, called the Zodiack, through which all the Planets
move; ſome of them ſeem to wander up and down this Line tranſverſe up
and down, but all come to the ſame end, with thoſe that keep a direct Line
that runs through this great Circle. The Sun keeps its conſtant Courſe
through a Line, called the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cliptick Line; we may imitate this Heavenly Body
in a conſtant even motion; ſome other Lights do move in the ſame Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,
but by their wandrings, are longer e're they perfect it: I find my ſelf
liable to wander <pb n="156" facs="tcp:151842:87"/>and ſtray, but I often pray, ſeek the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oul of thy Servant, O Lord, and I
beſeech thee, ſeek all thy ſtraying Sheep, gather them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one
Sheepfold, that every Creat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re, of
Things in Heaven, and Earth and under the Earth, may praiſe thee,
<hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega,</hi> Hallelujah, Hallelujah, Hallelujah,
<hi>Amen. Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:151842:87"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
